<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A spiritual legacy being a pattern of piety for all young persons practice in a faithful relation of the holy life and happy death of Mr. John Draper / represented out of his own and other manuscripts containing his experiences, exercises, self examinations and evidences for heaven ; together with his funeral sermons ; published by Chr. Ness.</title>
            <author>Ness, Christopher, 1621-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 186 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 103 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52818</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N464</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29558</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11169080</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11169080</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46511</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52818)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46511)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1426:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A spiritual legacy being a pattern of piety for all young persons practice in a faithful relation of the holy life and happy death of Mr. John Draper / represented out of his own and other manuscripts containing his experiences, exercises, self examinations and evidences for heaven ; together with his funeral sermons ; published by Chr. Ness.</title>
                  <author>Ness, Christopher, 1621-1705.</author>
                  <author>Draper, John, d. 1682.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[11], 190, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. Clark for the author and are to be sold by L. Curtis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata included at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Youth --  Religious life.</term>
               <term>Christian life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46511:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46511:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Spiritual Legacy; Being a PATTERN OF PIETY FOR ALL Young Perſons Practice, in a faithful <hi>Relation</hi> of the <hi>Holy LIFE</hi> and <hi>Happy DEATH</hi> OF M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> John Draper.</p>
            <p>REPRESENTED Out of his own and other Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripts; containing his <hi>Experiences, Exerciſes, Self-Examinations,</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences</hi> for <hi>Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with his <hi>Funeral SERMON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed by <hi>CHR. NESS,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by <hi>H. Clark,</hi> for the Author, and are to be ſold by <hi>L. Curtis,</hi> at Sr. <hi>Edmund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury Godfrey</hi>'s Head, near <hi>Fleet Bridge,</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:46511:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46511:2"/>
            <head>THE Epiſtle Dedicatory TO YOUNG MEN</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Boſom and beſt Beloved Diſciple ſaith,</hi> [I write to you Young Men, becauſe ye have overcome the wicked One, becauſe ye are ſtrong, and the Word of God abideth in you, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] 1 Joh. 2.13, 14. <hi>And poor I</hi> (<hi>the</hi> leaſt of Saints, <hi>and</hi> greateſt of Sinners) <hi>write accordingly unto</hi> you, <hi>that it may be ſo with you in this preſent Time, as it was with thoſe</hi> Young Men <hi>in the</hi> Primitive <hi>and</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical Times: <hi>What they (through Grace</hi>) did, <hi>and Had the honour of,
<pb facs="tcp:46511:3"/>the ſame ye ought to</hi> do, <hi>and</hi> have <hi>the like Ambition, both for</hi> Valour <hi>and for</hi> Victory: Solomon <hi>ſaith alſo, That the</hi> Glory of Young Men is their Strength, Prov. 20.29. <hi>The</hi> Hebrew <hi>word there for</hi> Young Men, <hi>ſignifeth</hi> Choice men, <hi>to wit, for</hi> Military Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, <hi>which may be underſtood in a</hi> Myſtical <hi>as well as in a Literal Senſe, ſeeing there is a</hi> Spiritual <hi>as well as a</hi> Temporal Warfare, Iſa. 40.2. 1 Cor, 9.7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2 Cor. 10.4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1 Tim. 1.18. <hi>There is the Figurative</hi> Fighting, <hi>the good Fight of</hi> Internal Faith, 1 Tim. 6.12. 2 Tim. 4.7. Heb. 10.32. <hi>As well as that which is</hi> Corporal <hi>by</hi> External Force: <hi>Nor can</hi> Young men <hi>be reputed more truly</hi> Valorous <hi>in any Heroick Exploits, than in Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhing the</hi> Prince of Darkneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O ye</hi> Young men, your Strength <hi>is indeed</hi> your Glory, <hi>and you are prone to</hi> Glory in your Strength <hi>as your pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Priviledge above all other Ages,
<pb facs="tcp:46511:3"/>but forget not that word of Wiſdom which tells you</hi> [Let not the mighty man Glory in his might, <hi>&amp;c. but</hi> let him that glorieth Glory in the Lord] Jerem. 9.23. 1 Cor. 1.31. <hi>And re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to uſe your ſtrength well, not in</hi> Quarrelling and Duelling (<hi>as thoſe Youngſters at</hi> Helketh-Hazzurim <hi>did, who ſheathed their Swords in each others Bowels, for a Play and Paſtime,</hi> 2 Sam. 2.14.16.) <hi>Not in</hi> Vanity <hi>or</hi> Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany, <hi>&amp;c. but in</hi> following <hi>your</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Callings, (<hi>as well as in</hi> fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for your native Countries, <hi>as thoſe</hi> Young men <hi>of the Princes of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces did,</hi> 1 Kings 20.20. <hi>from ver.</hi> 13, 14, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) <hi>As you are</hi> Strong Young men; <hi>more eſpecially in purſuing your</hi> General Calling, <hi>as you are Strong</hi> Young Chriſtians. <hi>Thus</hi> Young Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy <hi>became a</hi> good Souldier of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, 2 Tim. 2.3. <hi>not dreaming of any Carnal Delicacy, but</hi> Enduring Hardſhip, <hi>and living ſo abſtemiouſly among the luxrious</hi> Epheſians <hi>that the
<pb facs="tcp:46511:4"/>Apoſtle was conſtrained to preſcribe him Physick,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.23. <hi>As Godly</hi> Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy<hi>'s daily</hi> Task <hi>was to war a good marfare, ſo it ought to be</hi> yours.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>DIRECTIONS.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Make Religion <hi>your buſineſs,</hi> not a <hi>By-buſineſs;</hi> let it be jour <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha</hi> and your <hi>Omega, that</hi> muſt be in the <hi>Beginning</hi> and in the <hi>Ending,</hi> yea and in the <hi>Middle</hi> alſo of all your Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. Inure your ſelves ſo to it as to make it your familiar <hi>Exerciſe</hi> or <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation, Acts 24.16.</hi> Yea beſtirr your ſelves luſtily in it, as your buſineſs of greateſt Importance,<hi>1 Tim. 4.7.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Arm your ſelves with the whole <hi>Armour of God,</hi> both that part which is <hi>Defenſive</hi> (as the <hi>Girdle of Truth,</hi> the <hi>Helmet of Hope,</hi> the <hi>Shield of Faith,</hi> the <hi>Breaſt-Plate of Righteouſneſs,</hi> and the <hi>Shoes of Peace</hi> and <hi>Patience</hi>) And that alſo which
<pb facs="tcp:46511:4"/>is <hi>Offenſive,</hi> as the <hi>Sword of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> and <hi>Darts of Prayer,</hi> Eph. <hi>6.12, 13, to 19.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> In this Armour fight ye the <hi>good Fight of Faith, 1 Tim. 6.12.</hi> Be <hi>men of God,</hi> ver. <hi>11.</hi> and <hi>Quit your ſelves like men, 1 Cor. 16.13.</hi> Be more than men, <hi>be ſtrong, 2 Tim. 2.1.</hi> in the <hi>Grace which is by Je ſus Chriſt. Be Strong Young Men, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the Devil and he will flee from you, James 4.7. 1 Pet. 5.9.</hi> Satan is therefore but a Coward, who (like the <hi>Crocodile</hi>) when you follow him, he fleeth you, but if you flee from him, he followeth you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> In this Armour alſo do ye war a good warfare, <hi>1 Tim. 16.18.</hi> againſt thoſe <hi>Fleſhly Luſts, which war againſt your Souls, 1 Pet. 2.11.</hi> That like the <hi>Syrians,</hi> are commanded by their Maſter to <hi>war with neither Small nor Great,</hi> but with the <hi>King of
<pb facs="tcp:46511:5"/>Iſrael, 1 Kings 22.31.</hi> All their Spite is againſt the <hi>Soul,</hi> to deſtroy it and its <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Peace.</hi> If ſuch a Chaſt and Chaſtened peice as Mortified young <hi>Timothy</hi> was bid to <hi>Flee youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Luſts, 2 Tim. 2.22.</hi> How much more <hi>you in theſe debauching daies,</hi> and in your ſlippery Age, as ſlippery as Glaſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Tremble to turn This <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Armour</hi> into <hi>Carnal</hi> and <hi>Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feminate Amours:</hi> If you embrace <hi>Vice</hi> in your <hi>Youth,</hi> 'tis a thouſand to one but you will refuſe <hi>Vertue</hi> in your <hi>Old Age:</hi> Trees that bloſſom not in the <hi>Spring,</hi> will hardly bear fruit in <hi>Autumn.</hi> Beſides, is this fair dealing to give <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Devils</hi> leavings? How can God like to be Gleaning at laſt where the Devil hath been reapimg all your Time? to ſay nothing of the Strains and Cramps of Conſcience, which you will carry with you to your dying Day, as poſſibly you may do ſome ſtrains and cramps (while young and preſumptuous) in your body.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46511:5"/>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> But to be ſhort, conſider what <hi>Solomon</hi> (in his ſapiential Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, concerning the most ſoveraign good) ſaith by his moſt emphatical <hi>Irony</hi> for deterring all youngſters from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing ſenſual pleaſures <hi>[rejoyce O Young-Man in thy youth?]</hi> Eccles. <hi>11.9.</hi> That is <hi>[Do if thou dareſt]</hi> As <hi>God</hi> ſaid to <hi>Balaam [Go ſince thou wilt go.]</hi> Numb. <hi>22.20.</hi> But know that thou goeſt upon thy death. Thus this <hi>Ironical Conceſſion</hi> inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates that <hi>Young-Men</hi> have ſtrongeſt Inclinations to, and the ſtoutest Abilities for all kind of ſenſuallity, and they are moſt impatient both of reproof and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, therefore do they indulge their own jolly and frolick humours, in take<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their full of delights: <hi>In eating drinking, being madly merry,</hi> &amp;c. Let them do ſo (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) but at their peril. [<hi>But know,</hi> &amp;c.] O this ſtinging <hi>[But &amp;c.]</hi> marrs all their mirth, and is a <hi>Cooler</hi> to the <hi>Youngſters courage;</hi> one thought of
<pb facs="tcp:46511:6"/>an after reckoning ſpoils all his ſport, <hi>[For all theſe things]</hi> which are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted but <hi>Triffles</hi> and <hi>Tricks</hi> of <hi>Youth, [God will bring you to judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,]</hi> either in <hi>this life</hi> (as he did Young <hi>Abſolom</hi> and <hi>Adonijah, Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phineas, Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> and other Young Men, or however in the <hi>next life.</hi> Your <hi>Death Day</hi> ſhall unavoidably become your <hi>Dooms Day,</hi> then God will force you to appear before his dreadful tribunal, (though never ſo much againſt the hair and againſt the heart) thereto receive the direful ſentence of [<hi>go ye curſed</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Young-Men</hi> (of all men) are apteſt to put the evil day of death and judgment far from them: But this avails not any, yet undoes many, lul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them aſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ep in the cradle of ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. For (as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith) <hi>Senibus mors in Januis, Adoleſcentibus in inſidiis,</hi> Death is at the Door for old Men, yet lays in ambuſh for the young,
<pb facs="tcp:46511:6"/>and breakes oft in without knocking at the door, it oft comes like the lightning or thunder, both blaſting the green corn, and breaking yea burning down the neweſt and ſtrongeſt buildings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly.</hi> Let it be your <hi>care</hi> and your <hi>Conſcience</hi> to <hi>Remember your Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in the days of your youth, before the evil days of old age come upon you,</hi> Eccles. <hi>12.1.</hi> Sure I am, the ſtrongeſt obligations to this Duty lays upon you; for God is the firſt Author both of your <hi>being</hi> and <hi>well being,</hi> &amp;c. To forget him therefore (as the <hi>Wicked</hi> do and ſo <hi>are turned into Hell,</hi> Pſal. <hi>9.17.</hi>) is most <hi>Unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, Inhumane,</hi> and <hi>Diſingenious:</hi> Doe yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Remember your Maker</hi> prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically, ſo as to fear and love him, and faithfully ſerve him: Thus this <hi>Young-Man</hi> your pattern and my ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject here (I am perſwaded) did: You muſt accordingly <hi>ſerve God</hi> with the beſt of your time and ſtrength, while you are most able to do ſo, and
<pb facs="tcp:46511:7"/>have the best oppertunities, for poſſibly you may not live till old age. Go forth to gather <hi>Manna</hi> in the morning of your life, in the <hi>flower</hi> of your age, this will be most <hi>acceptable to God</hi> whoſe <hi>Soul deſireth the firſt ripe fruits,</hi> Mic. <hi>7.1.</hi> And who will remember <hi>the kindneſs of your youth</hi> in your remembring him, <hi>Jer. 2.1.</hi> This will be moſt <hi>Comfortable</hi> to <hi>your ſelves,</hi> knowing that you have mortified (in part through grace) thoſe impetuous paſſions, and inordinate affections, which drowns ſo many thouſands of Young-Men in the pit of perdition: O be not like the <hi>Circaſſians</hi> (a kind of <hi>Mongrel Chriſtians</hi>) who divide their lives betwixt <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>devotion</hi> dedicating their <hi>youth</hi> to <hi>rapine,</hi> and their <hi>old age</hi> to <hi>repentance, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erwoods inquiry, Pag. 135.</hi> But curſed be that cozener (faith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Mal. 1.14.) that hath a male in his flock, yet offereth to the Lord a corrupt thing.</hi> God likes not thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:46511:7"/>loiterers, that think to come into his Vineyard at the last hour of the day, to ſerve God then, when they can ſerve their luſts no longer. That would put off their Creator with the <hi>Dreggs</hi> and <hi>Snuffs</hi> of their time, when the <hi>Tempter</hi> hath taken the cream &amp; beſt: though your memoryes lay in the <hi>Hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der part of your Heads,</hi> yet may you not put off the <hi>Remembring your Creator</hi> to the <hi>Hinder part</hi> of your <hi>Lives,</hi> and poſſibly that may be Now, for aſſoon goes the Lambs skin to the market, as the old Sheep, let this <hi>young-Man,</hi> be a <hi>Pattern</hi> for your <hi>Practice:</hi> That your <hi>firſt fruits may ſanctify the whole lump, Rom. 11.16.</hi> that you may be the bleſſed Hope of another generation, <hi>1. King. 20.14.</hi> and that you may be <hi>delivered from wrath to come 1.</hi> Theſ. <hi>l. 10.</hi> Yea and be accounted worthy (with this dear one deceaſed) to inherit Glory is the unfeigned deſire of an Old Servant of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>CHR. NESS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:46511:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46511:8"/>
            <p>I Am this Day to Preach the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Sermon of a very Godly and Exemplar <hi>Young-man,</hi> who may be truly call'd [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] a <hi>Young Old Man</hi> (for his conſtant Grave Carriage, and Pious Deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) and that from a <hi>Text</hi> of <hi>his</hi> appointment, to wit,</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Geneſis,</hi> 47. Verſe 9.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>And</hi> Jacob <hi>ſaid unto</hi> Pharoah, <hi>the Days of the Years of my Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage are an Hundred and Thirty Years; few and evil have the Days of the Years of my Life been, and have not attained unto the Days of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:46511:9"/>the Years of the Life of my Fathers, in the Days of their Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>IT is a Dialogue 'twixt a <hi>Prince</hi> and a <hi>Patriarch.</hi> This Verſe, my <hi>Text,</hi> as it ſtands in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion with the <hi>Context,</hi> is the <hi>Patriarch</hi> Jacob's <hi>Anſwer,</hi> to <hi>King</hi> Pharoah's <hi>Queſtion,</hi> Verſe 8. Which was <hi>[How Old art thou?]</hi> Or, as the Hebrew Reading is, <hi>How many are the Days of the Years of thy Life?</hi> The <hi>Anſwer</hi> is, The Words of my Text aforementioned: The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Proſpect: whereof (omitting all unneceſſary Criticiſms and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſities upon the <hi>Text,</hi> as alſo, all Superfluous Circumlocutions upon the <hi>Context,</hi> which our narrow Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference of time cannot admit) propoſeth to our Conſideration theſe two <hi>particular parts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:46511:9"/>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The <hi>Poſitive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>Privative</hi> or <hi>Negative part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Poſitive part</hi> is, the True and juſt Account, that <hi>Jacob</hi> gives <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roah</hi> of the <hi>Nature, Quantity,</hi> and <hi>Quality</hi> of his Life or Converſe in the World, The Import whereof is this, <q>[Though I have lived ſo long as to reach up unto an Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and Thirty Years already, yet hath my Life been an Unſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and an Unſettled Life, and a continual <hi>Flitting,</hi> not only from one place to another, but alſo from one <hi>Affliction</hi> to another, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:46511:10"/>The <hi>Negative part</hi> is, The Dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Compariſon the <hi>Patriarch</hi> makes betwixt himſelf and <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple on the one hand, and his <hi>own Progenitors</hi> on the other, Intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that though at theſe my Years I ſeem very Old, as compared with the Short-liv'd <hi>Aegyptians;</hi> yet fall I far ſhort of the term of my Predeceſſors, both the <hi>Ante-dilu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vian</hi> and the <hi>Post-Diluvian Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though this Copious <hi>Text</hi> might be improved into a large Field of Diſcourſe, yet muſt I be confined to draw only ſome few, the moſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial, moſt Practical and Profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Corollaries,</hi> or <hi>Obſervations</hi> from the Circumſtances of it, with a ſhort Gloſs upon each [<hi>Tanquam Canis ad Nilum,</hi> only one lap and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46511:10"/>be gone] then improve them in ſome <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful Inferences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. Obſervation, <hi>From the Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Text.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt Remark</hi> or <hi>Obſervation</hi> ariſeth from the <hi>Perſon</hi> asking the Queſtion, (King <hi>Pharoah</hi>) is this;</p>
            <p>[<hi>As that King</hi> was <hi>Kind, Courteous,</hi> and <hi>Affable</hi> to Jacob <hi>for</hi> Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph's <hi>ſake,</hi> ſo <hi>all Kings ought</hi> to be the like to <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Seed, for <hi>Jeſus Sake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſame <hi>Pharoah</hi> was ſenſible how much both <hi>King</hi> and Kingdom were obliged to <hi>Joſeph,</hi> not only for <hi>Saving them all alive</hi> in the Famine, <hi>Gen.</hi> 50.20. but alſo for his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vaſt Additions of Wealth,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46511:11"/>Power, and Honour to the Crown of <hi>Aegypt, Gen.</hi> 47.20, 23, 24, 25. Therefore he gratefully acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth his Sentiments hereof in his ſhewing Reſpect to <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But when <hi>another</hi> Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roah <hi>aroſe after, who knew not</hi> Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph, <hi>Fxod.</hi> 1.8. That is, Ackno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged not any Obligations to him, though he fared the better for him in his Crown-Revenues, yet he ungratefully diſowned and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily Requited all <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Favours in the groſſeſt Unkindneſs to his People.</p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE.</head>
               <p>This teacheth by way of Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance, that all ſuch Kings as <hi>know not</hi> Joſeph <hi>or</hi> Jeſus (our Brother) are not only moſt unkind to, but alſo the moſt Severe Oppreſſors
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46511:11"/>of the Church. Though they have and Hold their Kingdoms by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment and Providence of <hi>Chriſt. Prov.</hi> 8.15. <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. Yet <hi>Chriſt's People</hi> Suffer hard things either by, or under them.</p>
               <p n="2">II. Obſervation, <hi>From the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of the Text.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Second Remark</hi> or <hi>Obſervation</hi> ariſeth from the Second Perſon in this Dialogue, who makes the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer</hi> to the <hi>Queſtion,</hi> to wit,</p>
               <p>[<hi>As this Perſon was</hi> Jacob, <hi>ſo his Days</hi> were <hi>few and evil, but</hi> as he was <hi>Iſrael, ſo his Days were many and good.</hi>]</p>
               <p>He had two Names <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Geneſis 49.1, 2. both gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him from his Wreſtling; the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46511:12"/>
                  <hi>farmer</hi> Name was given <hi>him</hi> for wreſtling with his <hi>Brother</hi> for the <hi>Birth-right</hi> in the Womb, wherein he Miſcarried; but the <hi>latter</hi> for his <hi>Wreſtling</hi> with his <hi>God</hi> for the <hi>Bleſſing</hi> at <hi>Penuel,</hi> wherein his Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour (through Divine Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) obtain'd the Victory. When the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> ſaw <hi>Jacob</hi>'s undaunted Courage in reſolutely detaining him, <hi>Asks him his Name,</hi> Gen. 32.24, 26, 27. As if he ſhould ſay, <q>[Thou art ſuch a Fellow as I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver met with, who though thou be <hi>lamed</hi> and laid Hard at, yet wilt not <hi>let me go without my Bleſſing;</hi> Thou haſt let thy Flocks go, and thy Herds go, Thou haſt let thy Wives go, and thy Children go, yet thou wilt not let me go, nor my Bleſſing go.]</q> 
                  <hi>I will not let thee go except thou Bleſs me,</hi> ſaith <hi>Jacob,</hi> v. 26. Hereupon
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46511:12"/>
                  <hi>He</hi> Honours <hi>Him</hi> (as it were) with the <hi>Honour of Knighthood,</hi> ſaying to him, [Kneel down <hi>Jacob,</hi> Riſe up <hi>Iſrael</hi>] for as a <hi>Prince, thou haſt had Power with God and with Men, and haſt prevailed.</hi> Gen. 32.28. Hoſ. 12.3, 4. Now <hi>Jacob</hi> is a Name of Weakneſs, the <hi>poor Worm</hi> Jacob, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.14. Trampled upon, and trodden under foot. This Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted State made <hi>Jacob</hi> ſigh out thoſe Sad Words <hi>[All theſe things are againſt me]</hi> Gen. 42.36. and thoſe of my Text alſo, <hi>[Few and Evil have the Days of the Years of my Life been.]</hi> But ſo far as he had <hi>Princely Power</hi> (as <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſignifies) both <hi>with God and with Men,</hi> In this Sence, his Days were <hi>many</hi> and <hi>good.</hi> One Day with <hi>God</hi> is a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand elſewhere.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="application">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:46511:13"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE.</head>
               <p>Hence learn we the Reaſon, why the <hi>Church</hi> is called <hi>Jacob</hi> through out the Scriptures, when Speech is of her <hi>Weakneſs and Calamity.</hi> But ſhe is frequently call'd <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to ſignifie her <hi>Splendour and Glory,</hi> and as it is thus with the <hi>Church of God</hi> in General, ſo it is with the <hi>Children of God</hi> in Particular. Some times they are run down with <hi>ſtrange Temptations,</hi> and with <hi>ſtrong Tribulations;</hi> then are they the <hi>poor Worm</hi> Jocob, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.14. The <hi>Shulamite found two Armies Warring in her,</hi> The <hi>Army</hi> of the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>Army</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> Cant. 6.13. When the Army of the Fleſh, or <hi>Amalek prevaileth,</hi> (as <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.11.) then the <hi>Seed of</hi> Jocob droops; but when they are made ſtrong in their
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:46511:13"/>Weakneſs, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. <hi>Strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with all Might,</hi> Col. 1.11. and made able (through the <hi>Supplies of Christ's Spirit</hi> Phil. 1.19.) <hi>to Tread down Strength,</hi> as <hi>Judg.</hi> 5.21. even the <hi>ſtrongeſt Temptation</hi> without, then are they called the <hi>Iſrael of God,</hi> Gal. 6.16. for their Prince-like prevailing over <hi>Fleſh, World, and Devil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. Obſervation, <hi>From the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the Text.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Third</hi> Obſervation ariſeth from the Conjunction of theſe two Parts, This <hi>Queſtion,</hi> and the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer</hi> to it, which is.</p>
               <p>['Tis a <hi>Duty Incumbent upon all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, to be Asking and Anſwering, How the Days of the Years of their Lives do paſs away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:46511:14"/>It was <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Prayer, <hi>Lord teach us to number our Days, that we may apply our Hearts unto Wiſdom,</hi> Pſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 90.12. In which <hi>Pſalm</hi> (it being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Meditation of Man's Mortality) cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſponding with my Text, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Mark</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Moſes</hi> mentions the Brevity and Uncertainty of Man's Life, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring it to a Watch, <hi>v.</hi> 4. which is but the fourth part of a Night <hi>Mark</hi> 13.35. Then he goes on and compares it to a <hi>Sleep,</hi> to a <hi>Dream,</hi> all vaniſhing things, and to a <hi>Tale</hi> that is ſoon told, and is as ſoon for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten; laſtly to <hi>Graſs,</hi> which, we well know, if it be not cut down in <hi>Summer</hi> or <hi>Autumn,</hi> doth wither in Winter. So ſuch Mortals as are not cut down with the Sithe of Death in their Youth, do yet wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther away in the Winter of Old Age. <hi>Quid eſt Vita, niſi quidam
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:46511:14"/>Curſus ad Mortem?</hi> ſaid the Ancient Father, <hi>Life is nothing but a Poſting to Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 2d. Occurrence in this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of <hi>Moſes</hi> upon Man's Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality is his aſſigning the proper pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing Cauſe of this Humane Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y to wit, Divine Diſpleaſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gainſt Sin, which cauſeth <hi>God</hi> to <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urn Man to Deſtruction,</hi> ver. 7, 8. <hi>Man</hi> at the firſt was made Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, he had then an <hi>Immortal Body,</hi> a Suitable Companion for his <hi>Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Soul.</hi> Theſe two Sweet Aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates had never been ſevered each from other, if <hi>Man</hi> had not ſinned againſt his <hi>Maker:</hi> Had <hi>Adam</hi> ſtood on his State of Innocency, <hi>He</hi> ſhould then have rendred to the Lord a time of perfect Obedience and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice here upon Earth, and when that Homage to his <hi>Great Landlord</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:46511:15"/>had been accompliſh'd, he ſhould then have been Tranſlated from <hi>Earth</hi> (without the leaſt <hi>taſte of Death</hi>) to Heaven; the <hi>Soul</hi> ſhould never have been ſeparated from the <hi>Body,</hi> as now it is; for the <hi>Wages of Sin is Death,</hi> Rom. 6.23. It was that <hi>one Man's</hi> Offence that pulled up the Sluce, and let in Death as a Deluge, with a Regal Authority over all the World, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.14, to 17. and <hi>Sin</hi> did not only let in <hi>Death</hi> but alſo all ſorts of Sickneſſes, Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, and Sufferings that are Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runners of it.</p>
               <p>Then 3ly, <hi>Moſes</hi> Condemns <hi>Mans Dulneſs</hi> in taking no more notice of this Divine Diſpleaſure, <hi>ver.</hi> 11. <hi>All other Creatures know their Times and their Seaſons,</hi> Jerem. 8.7. but <hi>Man knoweth not the Day of his Viſitation,</hi> till <hi>He come to be Snared in an Evil
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:46511:15"/>Net,</hi> &amp;c. Eccleſ 9.12. Though Man's Life be a Life full of all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies, of Indignities, of Injuries, of Infirmities, and of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities alſo, yet ſuch is the Stupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of the Fall'n Nature, that Man puts the Thoughts of theſe things far from him, <hi>Amos</hi> 6.3.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Hereupon <hi>Moſes</hi> begs God for Illuminating Grace wherewith to make a more Diſtinct Diſcovery of all Humane Frailty, [<hi>Lord teach w to number our Days,</hi> &amp;c.] ver. 12. And the <hi>Sweet-Singer of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>David,</hi> will be of the ſame <hi>Chorus</hi> with <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſighing, as well as ſinging out theſe Synonimical Sentences, [<hi>Lord make me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o know my end, and the Meaſure of my Days, what it is; That I may know how frail I am,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.4, 5. Thus like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Jacob</hi> in my Text carries on the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:46511:16"/>like Concord and Conſort to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat the Harmony, complaining here, [<hi>Few and evil have the Days of the Years of my Life been,</hi> &amp;c.] Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding only this one Note of Diſcord (for making better Muſick) that God had taught him this great Truth concerning his own Frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>He</hi> had ſeen it for time paſt, and <hi>He</hi> would be ſenſible of it for time to come, his <hi>Days</hi> had been <hi>few and Evil,</hi> Now they might be <hi>fewer</hi> and <hi>worſe,</hi> ſeeing <hi>He</hi> and <hi>all his</hi> were famiſhed out of <hi>Canaan,</hi> the Land of Promiſe, into <hi>Egypt,</hi> the place where his Poſterity would be <hi>evilly intreated.</hi> Gen. 15.13.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="application">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> teacheth us what uſe to make of the <hi>knowledge</hi> of our own <hi>Frailty.</hi> It ſhould ſtrongly ſtir us
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:46511:16"/>up to an earneſt imploring of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Mercy. He</hi> maketh a loud Out cry after <hi>Mercy.</hi> Crying, [<hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn O Lord, How long,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Oh ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie us early with thy Mercy,</hi> &amp;c.] <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.13, 14. He could find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in all the World but <hi>Divine Mercy</hi> to be a Congruous, and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Remedy,</hi> for <hi>Humane Malady</hi> and <hi>Mortal Miſery:</hi> And 'tis not a <hi>little of Mercy</hi> will do, but he muſt have <hi>much,</hi> even as much as will <hi>Satisfie,</hi> [<hi>Oh Satisfie,</hi> &amp;c.] The <hi>Salve</hi> muſt be ſuitable to the <hi>Sore</hi> for <hi>quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity,</hi> as well as <hi>quality; Great Miſery</hi> ſmarted under, requires <hi>Great Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> to Cure it. Yea, and he muſt have it <hi>early</hi> alſo, [<hi>Oh Satisfie me early,</hi> &amp;c.] The Soul of a Frail Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner (made ſenſible of his Sinful Frailty) even longs after Mercy; <hi>He cannot Live without it, he dare not Die without it,</hi> He muſt have
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:46511:17"/>Mercy (both the <hi>Giving</hi> and the <hi>Forgiving</hi> Mercy) whatever elſe he wants; 'tis the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num Neceſſarium,</hi> He muſt have it ſpeedily, or he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſit down ſatisfied. <hi>Valde prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatus ſum me nolle ſic a Deo Satiari:</hi> 
                  <q>God (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) ſhall not put me off with Pleaſure, Treaſure, Honour, or any thing below his Mercy. Mercy <hi>gives</hi> us <hi>much,</hi> yet <hi>forgives</hi> us <hi>more,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Fourth Obſervation</hi> ariſeth from the Body and and Subſtance of the Text, more to be inſiſted upon, to wit,</p>
               <p>Doctr. 4. <hi>[Man's Life is but a poor Pilgrimage.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis twice thus titled in my Text, <hi>Jacob</hi> calls his own Life <hi>a Pilgrimage,</hi> in the fore-part of it, and the Life
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:46511:17"/>of his Progenitors, he calls a Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage alſo in the latter part. The Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> moves a Parallel Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion to this of <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s. The lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter asks <hi>[What is your Age?]</hi> Gen. 47.8. and the former asks <hi>[What is your Life;]</hi> Jam. 4.14. This of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> admits of a double Anſwer.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Firſt</hi> is <hi>Philoſophical,</hi> And</p>
               <p>The <hi>Second</hi> is <hi>Theologicdl.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Firſt is that <hi>Anſwer</hi> which not <hi>Vain,</hi> but <hi>Solid</hi> and <hi>Sage Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy</hi> gives to the Apoſtles Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion <hi>[What is Man's Life?]</hi> to ſhew the <hi>Nature</hi> of it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Plato</hi> (that Divine Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher) calls Man's Life a <hi>Game at Dice,</hi> wherein what ſhall be the caſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:46511:18"/>[<hi>wore</hi> or <hi>leſs</hi>) is not in the Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Power, yet whatever is the caſt, 'tis the Gameſters Duty to make the beſt Improvement of it, that he may win the Game: This <hi>Platonick</hi> Notion carrieth a Correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondency with the <hi>Analogy of Faith,</hi> and with the <hi>Scripture of Truth,</hi> which ſaith [<hi>Mans ways are not in himſelf,</hi> &amp;c. [Jerem. 10.23. 'Tis indeed the Saying of ſome <hi>[quiſque ſuae Fortunae Faber] Every Man is the Framer of his own Fortune,</hi> which may be taken in <hi>Sano Senſu,</hi> if In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted only by that <hi>firſt Sermon</hi> (after <hi>that</hi> upon the Fall) which <hi>God</hi> (Himſelf) Preached to <hi>Cain,</hi> Gen. 4.7. <hi>If thou doſt well, Shalt thou not he accepted?</hi> But if thou <hi>Doſt ill, Sin lies at thy Door.</hi> Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, <hi>It is not in Man to direct his own Steps,</hi> faith <hi>Jeremy;</hi> much leſs to order the Succeſs of his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:46511:18"/>Works. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Man's Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> without <hi>God's Bleſſing cannot inrich,</hi> Prov. 10.4, 22. Man knows not therefore, what his <hi>Caſt</hi> ſhall be (more or leſs) in this Life, yet is it his Duty to make the <hi>Beſt</hi> and (if it be poſſible) a <hi>Bleſt</hi> Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all Occurrencies of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence attending him, That through Grace (which is the true <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pbers Stone,</hi> that turns all it touches into Gold) all Natural and Moral Evils may be converted into Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al good; This is the only way to win the beſt Game in the World. <hi>Vincenti Dabitur corona Vitae.</hi> The Winner's Wage is Eternal Glory, <hi>Revelat.</hi> 2.10, 17, 26. and 3.5.12.21.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Next to <hi>Plato,</hi> Hear <hi>Seneca.</hi> (Theſe two were the two <hi>great Luminaries</hi> of the <hi>Heathen
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:46511:19"/>World</hi>) who abounds in his <hi>Alluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> upon this Point. As</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. This <hi>Wiſe Moralliſt</hi> calls Man's Life a <hi>Warfare,</hi> wherein how ſoon our Enemy (Death) will come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, and overcome us, we know not, Therefore ſhould we be always upon our Watch, and Ward.</item>
                  <item>2. He compares Man's Life to a <hi>Flaſh of Lightning,</hi> which immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately <hi>appeareth,</hi> and as immediately diſappeareth again.</item>
                  <item>3. The Philoſopher comes up higher to the very Terms of our Text, and plainly ſaith, That <hi>Man's Life</hi> is but a <hi>Pilgrimage</hi> and Path<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to Death.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Some indeed ſay, That this ſame <hi>Seneca</hi> was acquainted with the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:46511:19"/>
                  <hi>Apoſtle Paul</hi> (his Contemporary in <hi>Nero's</hi> time) and that <hi>Epiſtles</hi> were writ from each to other, ſo might borrow ſuch Divine Notions from <hi>him:</hi> But ſure I am, <hi>he</hi> could not be Converſant with our Patriarch <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> unleſs in <hi>Moſes Pentateuch,</hi> from which <hi>he</hi> might borrow ſuch Sacred Phraſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as <hi>Homer</hi> did his <hi>Alcinous Garden,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Ovid</hi> his <hi>Deucalions Floud,</hi> &amp;c. from thence.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Pythagoras</hi> (Briefly of the reſt) compareth Man's Life to a <hi>Stage-play on a Theatre,</hi> where a Man acts his Part for a while, then reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, being diſ-attired or deveſted of all his Hiſtrionical Attire and Acting Garments.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, To this add that of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monides</hi> (Related by <hi>Rodulphus
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:46511:20"/>Agricola</hi>) who being askt, What <hi>Man's Life</hi> was? Anſwered with a Silent Sign, ſhewing himſelf to the Company a little while, and then with-drawing out of their ſight.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>Epictetus</hi> Declares <hi>Man's Life</hi> to be like a <hi>Voyage at Sea,</hi> upon the Narrow Seas, wherein he meets with High Winds, Rough Waters, Surging Waves, (as it were) all in a Conſpiracy to ſwallow him up; and if he eſcape the <hi>Storm,</hi> either Ragged Rocks, or Cruel Quick-Sands may Shipwrack him in a <hi>Calm.</hi> Yea, it may be, that <hi>Pyrates</hi> may plunder him, or ſome contrary Blaſts may blow him too ſoon to Shore: However, in thoſe <hi>Narrow Seas</hi> there is but a ſhort Cutt from Shore to Shore.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:46511:20"/>Many more Sayings of thoſe <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Sages</hi> might here be multiplied, were it not to avoid Prolixity.</p>
               <p>I have done with the <hi>Philoſophical Anſwer</hi> to [What is Man's Life?] Let us hear what is that which is <hi>Theological,</hi> that hath a more Noble Original, and is Taught in an Higher School: <hi>Picus Mirandula</hi> ſaith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently, that <hi>Philoſophy ſeeks Truth, Divinity finds it, and Piety poſſeſſeth it.</hi> The Notable Eſſays of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer have been heard, but <hi>Scripture Diſcovery</hi> is the <hi>more ſure Word of Prophecy, whereunto we ſhall do well to take heed,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.19.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Word of God</hi> aboundeth with many Metaphors to Illuſtrate the Nature of the <hi>Life of Man,</hi> being all Anſwers to the <hi>Apoſtles Queſtion
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:46511:21"/>[What is your Life?]</hi> I can but ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle forth ſome very few of them, that this narrow Diſcourſe ſwell not too much.</p>
               <p>The <hi>(Firſt)</hi> Reſemblance (wave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe I mention'd before from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90, &amp;c. which I inlarged on the more, becauſe 'tis a Paraphraſe on my Text) is that of the <hi>Apoſtle James</hi> who mov'd the <hi>Queſtion, What is your Life?</hi> And gives himſelf the <hi>Anſwer</hi> to it; no doubt, but well Accommodated, becauſe he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> to give it. <hi>He</hi> ſaith, <hi>[It is even a Vapour that appeareth for a while, and then va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth away]</hi> Jam. 4.14. Oh what a poor empty thing is a <hi>Vapour,</hi> no Solidity in it, 'tis not ſo much a <hi>Thing,</hi> as next to <hi>No-thing,</hi> It diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſeth it ſelf ſo ſoon as it is raiſed, no ſooner it <hi>appears,</hi> but it <hi>diſappears:</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:46511:21"/>Oh then, <hi>What a vain ſhew maketh Man</hi> in his Life. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.6. The Pomp of Great Princes <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Swoln Bubble, a <hi>big Phanſie,</hi> Act. 25.23.</p>
               <p>The <hi>(S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ond)</hi> Reſemblance is <hi>Smoak, My Days</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>are Conſumed like Smoak.</hi> Pſal. 102. 3. Good God, what a Vain thing is <hi>Life,</hi> if no better than <hi>Smoak!</hi> a <hi>Vapour</hi> may be lovely with its come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Colours, but <hi>Smoak</hi> is a Sooty thing, pleaſing to none, but offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to all; none thinks that <hi>Smoak</hi> is worth keeping, ſo <hi>Life</hi> may be as <hi>Smoak to the Eyes,</hi> burdenſome e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: Though the Flame of Fire be <hi>Smoak</hi> fired, yet the <hi>Smoak</hi> it ſelf hath not a Spark of fire in it; Thus this Temporal Life hath not ſo much as a Spark of Light, and Life in it compared with Eternity. Who can
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:46511:22"/>hold <hi>Smoak</hi> in his hand, or take and keep an handful of it? No more can he his <hi>own Life.</hi> Oh how <hi>Smoak</hi> haſtens up into the Heavens in its <hi>Rowling Pillars,</hi> and circular Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glomerations! ſo doth Man's Life to the Fountain of Life, fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whence it came: The <hi>Spirit returns to God,</hi> Eccleſ. 12.7.</p>
               <p>The <hi>(Third) Metaphor</hi> is a <hi>Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow,</hi> Man fleeth as a ſhadow, and continueth not, Job. 14.2. and Pſal. 112.11. A <hi>Shadow</hi> (we know) laſteth not long at any time, it can but laſt the length of a Day at the longeſt, for as ſoon as the <hi>Sun</hi> hides his Head under the <hi>Earth,</hi> die <hi>Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow</hi> is gone; But moſtly it laſteth but a little part of the Day, becauſe the Sun is oft hiding his Head un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Cloud, and ſo oft is the <hi>Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow</hi> gone; The <hi>Shadow</hi> of the Dyal
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:46511:22"/>haſteth to its Period, and who can ſtop it. So doth <hi>Man's Life,</hi> It <hi>fli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, as the Shadow of the Night before the Day,</hi> and <hi>as</hi> the <hi>Shadow</hi> of the Day, until Night returneth; The <hi>Shadow</hi> paſſeth along as the <hi>Body</hi> paſſeth, and who can hold it? but the Night cometh and taketh it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. Man carries an handful but of <hi>Smoak</hi> or of a <hi>Shadow,</hi> while he carries his Life in his hand. Oh what a poor handful is that which cannot be held! Oh how many (like <hi>Aeſop's Dog</hi>) do catch at this <hi>Shadow</hi> of a <hi>Temporal Life</hi> (which is ſlippery as Smoak or as a Shadow, ſo cannot be held, and oft ſo <hi>Vain</hi> and <hi>vexing,</hi> that 'tis not worth hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) neglecting in the mean time, that great Command <hi>[Lay faſt hold on Eternal Life.]</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.19.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:46511:23"/>The <hi>(Fourth)</hi> Similitude is, a <hi>Shepherds Tent [Mine Age is depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and removed from me, as a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds Tent]</hi> ſaith <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> I ſaiah 38.12. The <hi>Shepherd</hi> removes his <hi>Tent,</hi> as his Flock removeth from one place to another, and he can remove it eaſily and ſpeedily. Now the <hi>Lord is our Shepherd,</hi> Pſal. 23.1. and our <hi>Bodies</hi> are as ſo many <hi>Tents</hi> or <hi>Tabernacles.</hi> Bleſſed <hi>Paul</hi> (who was a <hi>Tent-maker,</hi> Act. 18.3.) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth the <hi>Body</hi> of Man to a <hi>Tent</hi> or (which is all one) to a <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. The <hi>Tent</hi> ſtands not, or falls not at its <hi>own,</hi> but at its <hi>own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> Pleaſure; ſo <hi>Man's Life</hi> is not at his <hi>own choice,</hi> but at <hi>God's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand;</hi> The <hi>Body</hi> is not call'd there a <hi>Temple</hi> (as <hi>Chriſt Body</hi> was, John 2.21. which could <hi>ſee no Corruption,</hi> Pſal. 16.10. &amp; Act. 13.35. but was
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:46511:23"/>to ſtand like a Stable <hi>Temple,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>God-head dwelt Bodily,</hi> Col. 2.9. For ever) but 'tis call'd an <hi>earthly Houſe,</hi> a ſhaken weather-beaten Houſe, a decaying Cottage, and a <hi>Tottering Tabernacle</hi> that muſt be taken down: God's own hand (that erected it) comes in a Fit of Sickneſs, and gently ſlackens the Cords, and .draws out the Pins that upheld this <hi>Tent,</hi> or <hi>Tabernacle;</hi> and ſometimes the Tent is blown down with ſome Blaſt of ſudden Death, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet if Godly to be raiſed again, is a more <hi>Glorious Pallace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>(Fifth) Compariſon</hi> is, the <hi>Shuttle of a Weaver,</hi> Job. 7.6. which in a moment paſſeth from one ſide of the Web to the other. The <hi>Shuttle</hi> hath a very ſudden Motion, and a very ſwift Paſſage from end to end, it ſtops not, till it (ordinarily)
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:46511:24"/>be through the Web, yet <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, <hi>[My Days are ſwifter than a Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver's Shuttle]</hi> that is, the time on my Life haſtens far faſter than <hi>it</hi> to its appointed Period: And <hi>Hezekiah</hi> compares God to a <hi>Weaver,</hi> and his! own <hi>Life</hi> to the <hi>Thread,</hi> which the Weaver cutteth off either when the Web is finiſhed, or before it comes to the Thrums, even at his Pleaſure, Iſa. 38.12. [<hi>He will cut off like a Weaver, my Life,</hi> &amp;c.] Before my <hi>Web</hi> be throughly wrought, before <hi>it</hi> reach the Thrums that are tyed to the Beam at the end of the Loom. The Blind Heathens did hammer at this great Truth, in their Fiction of the <hi>Three Fatal</hi> Siſters, <hi>Atropos, Clotho,</hi> and <hi>Lacheſis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clotho colum Bajulat, Lacheſis Trahit, Atropos Occat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:46511:24"/>
                  <hi>Clotho</hi> holds the Diſtaff, <hi>Lacheſis</hi> Spins out the Thread, and <hi>Atropos</hi> cuts it off at Pleaſure: As the <hi>Shut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> is caſt to and again and carries the Thread along with it forward and backward, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So is <hi>Man's Life</hi> toſſed too and fro, backward and forward, Night and Day, The Night caſts this <hi>Shuttle of Life</hi> to the Day, and the Day caſts it back to the Night again, but at length this tender Thread either breaks, or <hi>is cut off</hi> according to <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s Phraſe) and poſſibly the <hi>Weaver</hi> will cut the Web out of the Loom, before it be half accompliſh'd, as this <hi>Dead young Man</hi> may ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently demonſtrate: As to the Caſe of <hi>Hezekiah, He</hi> then thought his Thread had been in breaking, but <hi>God</hi> (the <hi>good Weaver</hi>) tyed the almoſt broken Thread again upon a <hi>Weavers</hi> Knot, ſo <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s Life
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:46511:25"/>became as an interrupted Web, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was woven on for Fifteen Year longer: And ſurely the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> forth the moſt Exquiſite Skill of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> excellent Weaver upon all thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whom he raiſed from <hi>Death to Life</hi> ſo made that tender Thread hold o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as firmly, as if it never had bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>cut off</hi> or <hi>broken. Lavater</hi> hath a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> uſeful Note upon thoſe two Texts o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the, <hi>Weaver's Shuttle,</hi> ſaying, [You that are <hi>Weavers,</hi> or but <hi>Lookers</hi> up on their Work] <hi>Meditate on your Mortallity,</hi> and your haſtening (as the <hi>Shuttle</hi>) to your End, and learn thence to <hi>live Holily,</hi> that you may <hi>Die Happily,</hi> for without <hi>Holineſs,</hi> you cannot have <hi>Happineſs.</hi> Hebr 12, 14.</p>
               <p>The <hi>(Sixth) Parallel</hi> (omitting the many more Metaphors occurring in Sacred Writ, of which ſome I
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:46511:25"/>may mention upon the next Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation) is that is may <hi>Text, [Man's Life is a Pilgrimage.]</hi> Sometimes the <hi>Scripture</hi> compares the <hi>Life of Man</hi> to a <hi>Voyage at Sea,</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to a <hi>Pilgrimage by Land,</hi> Theſe two are a Siſters, <hi>Synonoma's,</hi> and have the ſame Sence and Significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, thought in differing Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> As Man's Life is likened to a <hi>Voayage at Sea,</hi> ſo it repreſenteth, the Perils from <hi>Pyrates, Tempeſts,</hi> &amp;c. that Mortal Man is expoſed unto. <hi>[Is there not an appointed time]</hi> Job. 7.1. The <hi>Septuagint</hi> reads it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Locus Piratarum, Zanchy,</hi> a <hi>place of Pyrates,</hi> The <hi>Ship</hi> is never ſafe but in Harbour. But <hi>Job</hi> makes this Alluſion more plainly, ſaying, <hi>[My Days are paſſed away as the ſwift Ships.]</hi> Job. 9.26. Alas, how was
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:46511:26"/>poor <hi>Job</hi> as a Ship, <hi>toſſed with Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts and not comforted.</hi> Iſa. 54.11 till God brought him to the Haven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Man's Life</hi> as a Ship before the Wind, paſſeth on without any ſtay, until it come to Shore: Whether the Marriners in the Ship be ſleeping or wakeing, working or eating, ſhe runs on her courſe: So doth <hi>Man's Life</hi> run on, however he ſpends his time, whether he ſleeps or wakes, <hi>ſerves God, or ſerves the Devil,</hi> the Wind of Divine Power and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is carrying <hi>our Ship of Life</hi> nearer its <hi>Port,</hi> while I am thus Speaking <hi>and you Hearing,</hi> God grant <hi>it</hi> may be the <hi>Cape of Good Hope, Heaven,</hi> to wit, the beſt landing place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> As <hi>Man's Life</hi> is likened to a <hi>Pilgrimage by Land,</hi> ſo this likewiſe declares it to be a Perilous Paſſage and Path-way. We muſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:46511:26"/>not take the Word <hi>[Pilgrimage]</hi> in the Text either <hi>ſtrictly,</hi> or <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiouſly</hi> in the ſence of the <hi>Popiſh Votaries, Jacob</hi> was not to be looked upon (no not by <hi>Pharoah</hi> himſelf) to be a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Pilgrim, nor any of the Holy <hi>Patriarchs</hi> his Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors: The <hi>Popiſh Pilgrimage</hi> to <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> is a <hi>Ridiculous,</hi> as well as a <hi>Superſtitious</hi> Practice, for no one place can bring a <hi>Man</hi> nigher <hi>God,</hi> than another, all parts of the <hi>Earth</hi> have an equal diſtance from <hi>Heaven;</hi> though the <hi>Romanists</hi> plead, that Father <hi>Cyril</hi> went thither, yet <hi>he</hi> himſelf profeſſeth, that <hi>he</hi> went not upon the account of any private Pilgrimage to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but as <hi>he</hi> was ordered by Publick Authority to viſit the <hi>Eaſtern Churches,</hi> and to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh <hi>them</hi> in the Truth. But we muſt underſtand <hi>Pilgrimage</hi> here <hi>largely,</hi> for a <hi>Path-way</hi> a <hi>Thorough-Fare,</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:46511:27"/>a <hi>Courſe, Race,</hi> or <hi>Journey,</hi> from one place to another. Thus a <hi>Pilgrim</hi> in Scripture-Sence is all one with a <hi>Traveller, a Stranger,</hi> and a <hi>Sojourner; Man's Life</hi> is but his <hi>walk</hi> and <hi>way.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There be many <hi>Congruities</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, which I ſhall reſerve to diſcourſe upon in handling the <hi>Sixth Obſervation,</hi> as being their proper place, adding only here, that there is a <hi>Two-fold Pilgrimage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> A <hi>Natural Pilgrimage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> A <hi>Moral Pilgrimage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> The <hi>Natural Pilgrimage</hi> is the <hi>courſe</hi> that a <hi>Man</hi> rides, the Race that he runs, even the whole Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage and Progreſs of his Life of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>[ab <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tero ad <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rnam]</hi> from <hi>his
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:46511:27"/>Birth</hi> to <hi>his Burial,</hi> for till then he comes not to his Journeys end, or to the Period, or <hi>full Point of his Pilgrimage,</hi> There be two Terms in this <hi>former,</hi> to wit, the <hi>Grave of the Womb</hi> is the <hi>Terminus a quo,</hi> or ſtarting place, <hi>Man</hi> begins this <hi>Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage</hi> as ſoon as he is Born of a Woman, and comes out of the Womb into the World, and <hi>he</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver reſts from his Travel (but is a poor Pilgrim ſleeping and waking) until he come to reſt in the <hi>Womb of the Grave:</hi> There the <hi>weary be at Reſt.</hi> Job. 3.17. that is, <hi>His Termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ad Quem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is <hi>Secondly,</hi> a <hi>Moral Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage,</hi> wherein likewiſe there are two the like <hi>Terms,</hi> This is a walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from our <hi>ſelves,</hi> and from our Sins, up unto <hi>God</hi> and unto <hi>Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> The <hi>beginning</hi> of this <hi>Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:46511:28"/>(Morally taken) is the priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive part [a <hi>ceaſing from Sin,</hi> or <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting from Evil]</hi> and the <hi>Accomplishment</hi> of it is the <hi>poſitive part</hi> [<hi>a Learning to do well,</hi> and not only a <hi>purſuing,</hi> but alſo an <hi>overtaking of that which is Good</hi>] Iſa. 1.16, 17. and Pſal. 34.14. and Amos 5.15. And this is a <hi>Metaphorical Walk, non Pedibus, ſed Affectibns,</hi> as ſaith the <hi>Father,</hi> with our <hi>Affections</hi> (Thoſe <hi>Feet</hi> of the <hi>Soul</hi> whereby <hi>it</hi> goes forth after Objects) more than with <hi>thoſe of the Body.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="application">
               <head>I. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Seeing your <hi>Life</hi> is but a <hi>Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage,</hi> a <hi>coming</hi> and a <hi>going,</hi> as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>'s Phraſe is, and of <hi>Joſhuah</hi> before him <hi>[Behold I am going the way of all the Earth]</hi> 1 King. 2.2. and Joſh. 23.14. that is, The way of all the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:46511:28"/>Men upon Earth, who are all doom'd to go that way. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.27. Oh conſider, both you <hi>young,</hi> and you <hi>old,</hi> your Life is a <hi>Path-way</hi> either to a <hi>Priſon,</hi> or to a <hi>Pallace,</hi> it is a Thorough-Fare either to <hi>Heaven</hi> or to <hi>Hell:</hi> Bethink your ſelves in time: Be Men and Women of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration,</hi> for <hi>that</hi> is it which diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes <hi>Men</hi> from <hi>Beaſts,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="application">
               <head>II USE.</head>
               <p>Then <hi>Agree with your Adverſary</hi> (an angry God for your Sins) <hi>while you are in the way</hi> of your Life, Matth. 5.25. While you are going your Pilgrimage, before you come to the <hi>Judges Houſe,</hi> who will certainly ſend you (if <hi>unreconciled</hi>) into an Everlaſting Priſon: If you walk in the <hi>broad way,</hi> being all for Elbow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>room to Sin, and leading looſe and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:46511:29"/>Licentious Lives, you are haſtening down to the <hi>Chambers of Eternal Death</hi> Matth. 7, 13. but if in the <hi>Narrow-way,</hi> of a ſtrict: Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Then are you going to a <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace,</hi> not to a <hi>Priſon,</hi> ver. 14. a good Life always beſpeaks a good Death, and all Perſons are paſſing either to <hi>Heaven</hi> or <hi>Hell</hi> while they live, and when they Die, their Death is but a flitting to the <hi>one place</hi> or to the <hi>other,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Having thus far diſcovered the <hi>Nature</hi> of Humane Life, defined or deſcribed in the <hi>Text</hi> to be, not any <hi>Royal Progreſs</hi> (which is conſtantly carry'd on, and manag'd after a Splendid manner, every way adap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Grandeur of Majeſty) No, the Life of Man hath no ſuch ſtately Proſpect in this Holy <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs</hi> eye, but 'tis a <hi>poor Pilgrimage,</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:46511:29"/>twice inculcated here, and as oft aggravated with contemptible Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances relating to both the <hi>Quantity,</hi> and the <hi>Quality</hi> of this <hi>poor Pilgrimage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From tke former of theſe two (to wit, the <hi>Quantity</hi>) ariſeth my <hi>Fift Obſervation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doctr. 5. [The <hi>Pilgrimage of Man's Life is but a ſhort Pilgrimage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus this Bleſſed <hi>Patriarch</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted his own Life in the Text to be but a <hi>ſhort Life</hi> conſiſting only of a <hi>few Days,</hi> though he had now at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to the Age of <hi>an Hundred and Thirty years:</hi> [<hi>Few and evil,</hi> &amp;c.] To ſpeak diſtinctly of the [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] that it is ſo; of the [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] why it is ſo; and of the [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how it is ſo, cannot be expected
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:46511:30"/>in this ſhort Diſcourſe, ſave only ſome promiſcuous Intimations of them all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="reason">
               <head>I. REASON.</head>
               <p>The <hi>ſhortneſs</hi> of this <hi>Pilgrimage</hi> is Demonſtrable three ways.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> In as much as <hi>Man's Life</hi> is meaſured by <hi>Days</hi> (one of the leaſt Computations of time) not by <hi>Weeks,</hi> or by <hi>Months,</hi> much leſs by <hi>Years.</hi> Thus <hi>Jacob</hi> computeth his own Life by Days in the Text twice over, as <hi>he</hi> doth alſo the Lives of the foregoing <hi>Patriarchs.</hi> Thus <hi>Job</hi> likewiſe numbereth his <hi>Life</hi> by <hi>Days</hi> over and over again, as <hi>Job</hi> 7.1.6. and 14.1.5. and many more places, too long to enumerate. So <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.1.4. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.3.11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yea, and all the moſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:46511:30"/>Mortified Men in Scripture do una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly concur in the ſame Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of their <hi>Lives by Days.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="reason">
               <head>II. REASON.</head>
               <p>The (Second) Demonſtration that <hi>Man's Life is ſhort,</hi> as it is <hi>meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> ſo it is <hi>numbered</hi> by his Days, yea to be but as one day. Becauſe it conſiſts only of a <hi>few Days,</hi> This <hi>Epithet</hi> is expreſſed in the Text, [<hi>Few are my Days,</hi> &amp;c.] Man's appointed <hi>Time</hi> is but a <hi>few Days,</hi> Job. 7.1. and 14.13.14. A <hi>few Days</hi> are the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>of his Life,</hi> Pſal. 39.4. Yea, the <hi>Days of an Hireling,</hi> who is hired only for ſome <hi>few Days</hi> to do ſome Jobb of Work which requireth haſte, and is but for a Spurt, not laſting: Nay, Sometimes the Hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is hired but for one <hi>ſingle Day,</hi> as <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.1, 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:46511:31"/>
                  <hi>Parable</hi> calls <hi>Man's Life</hi> but one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Day, conſiſting of twelve Hours. And what a poor part of time is one Day, eſpecially when <hi>the</hi> Sun <hi>Sets at the Noon of that Day.</hi> Amos 8.9. This makes it a very <hi>ſhort Pilgrimage</hi> indeed, as was that of this <hi>Young-man.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="reason">
               <head>III. REASON.</head>
               <p>The (Third) Demonſtration is drawn from Scripture Metaphors which Illuſtrate the <hi>ſwiftneſs</hi> of Man's Life in its Paſſage through the World, all implying the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of that Paſſage, for the <hi>ſwifter,</hi> that the Motion of the Runner is, the ſhorter is the time wherein the Race is run.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:46511:31"/>I might Re-aſſume here, the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophical Alluſions</hi> of Man's Life, As,</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Plato's Game at Dice,</hi> is ſoon play'd out.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Seneca</hi>'s <hi>Flaſh of Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> ſoon vaniſheth.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Pythagoras</hi>'s <hi>Stage play</hi> is ſoon Acted.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>Symonide</hi>'s ſhewing his <hi>Face,</hi> ſoon ſhewed his Back and was gone.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>Epictetus</hi>'s <hi>Voyage</hi> is very ſhort, and all the former are ſhort, none of them long abiding.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:46511:32"/>So likewiſe the <hi>Theological,</hi> As
<list>
                     <item>l. <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>Vapour</hi> ſoon Evapora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>David</hi>'s <hi>Smoak</hi> ſoon Dwind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth.</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Job</hi>'s <hi>Shadow</hi> ſoon Vaniſheth.</item>
                     <item>4. <hi>Hezekiah's Tent</hi> is ſoon taken down.</item>
                     <item>5. And both <hi>Job</hi> and <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s <hi>Shuttle</hi> hath both a <hi>ſwift and</hi> a <hi>ſhort</hi> Motion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6. The <hi>Prophet's Grafs</hi> ſoon <hi>wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth,</hi> and his <hi>Flower</hi> ſoon <hi>fadeth,</hi> The Time for all theſe is but a <hi>ſhort Time,</hi> as ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle [The time is ſhort]</hi> 1 Cor. 7.29.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:46511:32"/>But to inſiſt only upon thoſe three great <hi>Metaphors</hi> that <hi>Job</hi> ſeriouſly plays upon all together <hi>[a Poſt, a ſhip, and an Eagle]</hi> Job 9. 25, 26. to ſhew the <hi>ſwiftneſs</hi> and (thereby) the <hi>ſhortneſs</hi> of his own Life or Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage.</p>
               <p>The Improvement of theſe three Points muſt ſtand here for a <hi>Third Application.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Firſt Simile.</p>
               <p>The <hi>First</hi> Metaphor Reſembleth <hi>Man Riding Poſt,</hi> [<hi>My Days an ſwifter than a Poſt,</hi> &amp;c.] which Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion hath a fourfold <hi>Congruity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, As the <hi>Poſt-Boy</hi> is one that Rides upon Swift Horſes, <hi>ſpurring</hi> them End-ways, and ſparing no
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:46511:33"/>
                  <hi>Horſe-ſteſh,</hi> Riding always upon the Speed, with <hi>Haſte, Haſte, Haſte</hi> for His Majeſties Service, from City to Country, and from one Kingdom to another, carrying always Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Great Concern along with him: So every Man is Riding Poſt in this Life, carry'd in the <hi>Chariot of Time,</hi> which is drawn by the <hi>ſwifteſt Horſes,</hi> even ſuch as be <hi>Winged Horſes</hi> like <hi>Pegaſus,</hi> and ſo <hi>Flee fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter than any Poſt,</hi> according to <hi>Job's</hi> Phraſe <hi>[My Days are ſwifter than a Poſt, They flee away, &amp;c.]</hi> They run faſter, and outrun the Poſt. Oh that <hi>Men would conſider</hi> the great Concern of the Pacquet they carry, and the Tendency of their <hi>way,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Bethink your ſelves,</hi> 2 Chron. 6.37. (as the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Reading is) and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Septuagint</hi> Reads Pſal. 119.59. Make a Dialogue with your own Hearts, <hi>commune with them
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:46511:33"/>upon your Beds;</hi> as <hi>David</hi> did, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Excutite, Excutite,</hi> Zeph. 2.1. <hi>Shake your ſelves from</hi> Sluggiſhneſs, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did, Judg. 16.20. <hi>Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> and <hi>better conſider,</hi> Hagg. 1.5, 7. do it not to half part.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The <hi>Poſt</hi> Rides Night and Day without either ſtop or ſtay, making no long Meals any where, but takes a Bit and away, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So <hi>Man's</hi> Life is ever in motion, it makes no ſtands at any place or time, but every Moment he is yielding ſome little unto Death, his Life is paſſing towards it, while <hi>he</hi> is ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Bed; He is ever Riding Poſt, be it <hi>Winter</hi> or <hi>Summer</hi> time, or be his <hi>way</hi> and <hi>weather</hi> fair or foul, in <hi>Proſperity</hi> or <hi>Adversity.</hi> Oh <hi>that there were ſuch an Heart in</hi> Men <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.29. to <hi>conſider their latter end.</hi> Deut. 32.29. Seeing every
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:46511:34"/>
                  <hi>Year, Month, Week, Hour</hi> and <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute,</hi> you are riding Poſt to your Graves. They that do not <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber their latter end,</hi> are to be <hi>lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> becauſe they will <hi>come down wonderfully,</hi> Lament. 1.9.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, The <hi>Poſt</hi> is Betruſted with Matters of weightieſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſometimes the <hi>ſaving</hi> or <hi>ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of a Kingdom depends upon the <hi>Poſts Carriage</hi> or <hi>Miſcarriage; he</hi> therefore (in ſuch a Caſe) is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to Ride upon pain of Death, and dare not loiter, or linger care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly, till he come at the end of the Stage, and till his Pacquet be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully delivered: So <hi>Man</hi> in his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Poſt</hi> is betruſted with a concern of Infinite and everlaſting Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, to wit, his <hi>Pretious Soul,</hi> which is a <hi>Jewel</hi> of more <hi>worth than the whole World; Chriſt</hi> (who is
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:46511:34"/>
                  <hi>Truth</hi> it ſelf) ſaith ſo, and he is beſt able to know the <hi>worth of Souls,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he alone paid the price of Souls. <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.26. and 20.28. Oh <hi>conſider,</hi> how everyone of you are Riding Poſt with this <hi>Pearl of great Price</hi> in your hands, take heed of ſcattering it, or trucking it away for Traſh and Trifles; you Ride up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pain of Death, be not careleſs, your <hi>Life Spiritual and Eternal</hi> lies at Stake; how can you be too care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful? beware of Spiritual Slumber, until your <hi>pretious Pacquet</hi> be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon a Dying Bed, and you then be able to ſay with the Proto-Martyr <hi>Stephen, [Lord Jeſus, Receive my Spirit]</hi> Act. 7.59. or better with your <hi>Bleſſed Redeemer,</hi> ſaying <hi>[Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, into thy hands I commend my Spirit]</hi> Luke 23.46. Thus <hi>David</hi> was careful to deliver his Pacquet
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:46511:35"/>into Right hands both <hi>Living</hi> and <hi>Dying.</hi> Pſal. 31.5, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, Some <hi>Poſts</hi> Ride <hi>longer</hi> Stages than others, and ſome <hi>ſhorter</hi> with their Mail, and Errand; yea, ſome are ſtopp'd and Robb'd of their Charge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus no Man knows the length of his Poſt-Stage: We know, that it is but ſhort in <hi>General,</hi> but alas, we know not how ſhort it may be in <hi>particular:</hi> We are bid <hi>[not to Boast of to Morrow, for we know not what a Day may bring forth]</hi> Prov. 27.1. Jam. 4.13. Matth. 6.34, We know not what lies hid in the Womb of Time, one Big-belly'd Day may diſmount us: as <hi>young</hi> as we, as <hi>ſtrong</hi> as we have been diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted; yea, ſome we ſee daily are <hi>unhorſed</hi> aſſoon as thy ſet out, dying in their. Child-hood: God call'd from Heaven to <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:46511:35"/>
                  <hi>[Stay now thy ſtriking] Gent</hi> 22.10, 11. and he may call upon any one of us. this or the next Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſaying <hi>[Stay now your Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding]</hi> God (indeed) gives to ſome enough of <hi>Riding Poſt,</hi> they are weary with <hi>Poſting,</hi> weary of the World, and the World as weary of them, they <hi>live undeſired</hi> and <hi>die un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamented:</hi> But all muſt <hi>wait till their change come.</hi> Job 14.14.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Second Alluſion</hi> in Job 9.26. is a Man <hi>Sailing in a Ship.</hi> Mark the <hi>Gradation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Second Simile.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt, A Ship is ſwifter</hi> than a <hi>Poſt,</hi> and thence <hi>Job</hi> riſeth higher there; but an <hi>Eagle</hi> is ſwifteſt of all the three: A <hi>Ship</hi> paſſeth ſwiftly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Wind, and ſtoppeth, ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:46511:36"/>not, till ſhe come to the Shore, ſome one Port, ſhe is <hi>Bound</hi> for and reſts not, ſtrikes not Sail, till ſhe reach her deſired Harbour or Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
               <p>Mark alſo the <hi>Congruity</hi> in ſundry Particulars betwixt <hi>Man's Paſſage through this Life,</hi> and a <hi>Ships paſſing through the Sea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>(Firſt)</hi> Congruity is, as a <hi>Ships Bulk</hi> (being built juſt after the manner of <hi>Man's Body</hi> in a Supine poſture, the Bottom-Tree anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Back-Bone which hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ribs riſing up on both ſides, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) is made for <hi>Motion,</hi> not <hi>Reſt.</hi> Hence the <hi>Ignorant Indians</hi> call'd the firſt ſhips they beheld <hi>[Moving Iſlands]</hi> All ſhips are made for launching out into the <hi>Deep Waters.</hi> Pſal. 107.23, 24. And when heaved from off the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:46511:36"/>Stocks (where they are built) in order to their paſſing down into the Deep, have a peculiar Name (as the <hi>Good-Speed,</hi> the <hi>Adventure,</hi> &amp;c.) put upon them: Even ſo it is with the poor <hi>Iſle of Man,</hi> (ſo called) he upon his firſt Launching forth from his Mothers Womb, into a Sea of miſery, hath ſome ſignificant Name put upon him, with many hearty wiſhes (from Parents and Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) ſent after him, both for his <hi>Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and <hi>Succeſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, No ſooner is the <hi>Ship</hi> Launched out into the Main Ocean, but ſhe meets with contarry Winds, raging Waves, dreadful Storms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as before; ſo that ſhe is never ſafe or quiet till ſhe reach her Reſt, in her <hi>deſired Haven,</hi> Pſal. 107.30. Thus it is with <hi>Man,</hi> while in this lower World) the <hi>place</hi> of <hi>Pyracy,</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:46511:37"/>Job 7.1. <hi>ut ſupra.</hi>) He is aſſaulted with many Pyrates (who hang out falſe Colours, to decoy him within the Command of their Cannons) <hi>He is Afflicted, toſſed with Tempests,</hi> and <hi>not Comforted,</hi> Iſa. 54.11. This preſent evil World is a very <hi>Shop, fully furniſhed</hi> with All Tempting Tools, and the <hi>life of man</hi> is but as one Temptation, continued from Firſt to Laſt: 'Tis a <hi>life</hi> made up all of Temptation. <hi>Man</hi> is ever under either <hi>Viſible</hi> or <hi>Inviſible</hi> Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers: He paſſeth through Perils (<hi>in Perils often,</hi> as <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26.) every moment , untill he Reach to that Everlaſting Reſt, in a <hi>Deſired Haven,</hi> Heb. 4.9. Revel. 14.13.</p>
               <p>The <hi>(Third) Congruity</hi> is, A <hi>Ship</hi> is not only made for <hi>Motion,</hi> but for <hi>Swift Motion.</hi> Hence <hi>Job</hi> phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:46511:37"/>it <hi>[My days paſs away, as the Swift Ships]</hi> Hebr. <hi>Ships of</hi> Ebeck, which may be read <hi>[Ships of deſire]</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be <hi>Ships of Pleaſure,</hi> or <hi>Yatches,</hi> which are Built <hi>Frigat-wiſe,</hi> for <hi>Sayling Swiftly:</hi> Or they be <hi>Ships of Pyracy</hi> (as <hi>Mendoza</hi> reads it, ſaying, <hi>[Naves Piraticae &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibus Vacuae quam velociſſime Rapiun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur]</hi> Plundering and Pilfering <hi>Privateers,</hi> being empty of Burdens, make the moſt ſpeedy way, in Plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing through the Waters; eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when they have both Wind and Tide with them, to promote their Progreſs: Thus it is with poor mortal Man, who is a rowling, tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling thing, like a <hi>Ship,</hi> hopping from <hi>Hill to Mountain,</hi> and meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with no <hi>Reſting Place,</hi> Jer. 50.6. <hi>He reels to and fro, as if drunk,</hi> like the Marriners in a toſſed Ship, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.26, 27. Yea, and many mens
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:46511:38"/>motions to <hi>Hell</hi> are as <hi>ſwift Ships,</hi> making <hi>great haſte thither,</hi> Prov. 1.16. Iſa. 59.7. Rom. 3.15. <hi>mans life</hi> is <hi>ſwift</hi> of it ſelf, but it runs moſt ſwiftly when the wind of Temptation and the tide of Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion concurr to carry it forward &amp;c. Oh would to God the motions of your minds, made as much expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition towards <hi>Heaven,</hi> as <hi>wicked men</hi> do towards <hi>Hell:</hi> All men are <hi>Ships</hi> of <hi>Deſire,</hi> both good and bad, All are Home-bound to one of thoſe <hi>ports;</hi> and never do the winds ſo much fill the Sails of ſuch and ſuch a Ship, as <hi>Deſires</hi> do fill the minds of the Mariners to be at ſuch and ſuch a <hi>Deſired Haven:</hi> 'Tis true, the worſt of wicked men do not <hi>Deſire Hell,</hi> yet though they do not deſire <hi>that end,</hi> they have ſtrong deſires towards <hi>the way</hi> to that end; how ought every <hi>gracious ſoul</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:46511:38"/>to pray for the freſh gales of <hi>Gods Spirit: John</hi> 3.8. and to cry with the Spouſe in the Song [<hi>Awake O Northwind, and come thou Southwind, blow upon me,</hi> &amp;c.] <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.16. a Godly Perſon hath with <hi>Paul</hi> his <hi>[Cupio Diſſollvi]</hi> a deſire to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved and to be with <hi>Chriſt, Phil.</hi> 1.23. O how ſhould we all (with the <hi>penitent prodigal, Haſten home to our Fathers Houſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Luke</hi> 15.17, 18, 20. <hi>Heaven</hi> is our home, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. from 1. to 7. 'tis our <hi>Deſired Haven, Pſal.</hi> 107.30. even everlaſting happineſs.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, the <hi>(Fourth)</hi> paraphraſe upon <hi>Jobs phraſe</hi> (that mans life is like a Ship) followeth, that as a Ship leaves no viſible tract behind her, ſo life <hi>paſſeth unto death, and the memory of it is forgotten.</hi> Solomon ſaith, <hi>the way of a Ship in the midſt of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:46511:39"/>the Sea cannot be tracked, Prov.</hi> 30.19. for though ſhe make deep furrows in her paſſage all along, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> do they immediately cloſe up again and the ſame <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith of men, yea of great men (that carry a great figure in their place, and be of a Ruffling grandeur in the world) when once Dead, the memory of them wears out of the mind, <hi>Eccles.</hi> 8.10. and 9.5. Thus <hi>Aegypt</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat <hi>Joſeph, Exod.</hi> 1.18. and <hi>Iſrael Gideon, Judg.</hi> 8.34, 35. <hi>Yea men, Friends and Familiars remember the dead no more.</hi> Thus likewiſe ſome underſtand that phraſe in Dan. 8.5. <hi>[The he goat toucheth not the ground]</hi> in this ſence that it imports, not only the ſpeed and expedition of <hi>Alexanders</hi> prodigious conqueſts, but alſo that in a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhort time no man would know what was become ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of that great conqueror, or
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:46511:39"/>of any of his vaſt Conqueſts, there would be no print of any their foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps left behind , they would no more be found than <hi>the way of a ſhip in the midſt of the Sea.</hi> Yet O how good it is to be a godly perſon for <hi>the Righteous ſhall be had in Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Remembrance, Pſal.</hi> 112.6. <hi>the memory of the juſt full be bleſſed., Prov.</hi> 10.7. they ſhall be menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned with much veneration, after death, even by thoſe that ſpared not to Reproach them in their life; their very name ſhall be honourable and acceptable to God and men; whereas the <hi>name of the wicked rotteth,</hi> and ſtinks above ground, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.7.</p>
               <p>Fifthly and laſtly, a Ship never reſts, till ſhe come into her deſired Heaven, ſo mans life ſtays no where till it comes to its long reſt, and that is a bleſſed reſt to thoſe that <hi>dye in
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:46511:40"/>the Lord, Revel.</hi> 14.13. <hi>that fall aſleep in Jeſus,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.14. God takes a way their Souls out of their bodies (as it were) by a Kiſs; thus Rabins read that phraſe [<hi>Gnal pi Jehovah] Deut.</hi> 34.5. <hi>at the mouth of the Lord</hi> Moſes <hi>dyed</hi> (not, as we, according to the words of the Lord) As if God had taken away his Soul with a kiſs of his mouth; ſuch a kiſs of love as the Spouſe prayed for; from the mouth of Chriſt, <hi>Cant</hi> 1.2. when this is done what follows after but reſt from labours? (1) from <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of neceſſity</hi> (2) from <hi>labours of Infirmity,</hi> and (3) from <hi>labours of Iniquity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">(1.) They Reſt from the <hi>firſt,</hi> to wit, the <hi>Neceſſary</hi> yet toilſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Labours of this Life; they take no more thought <hi>[Propoter Victum &amp; Amictum]</hi> what they ſhall eat, drink,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:46511:40"/>or put on : They hunger and thirſt no more; they are then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>as the Angels,</hi> that need no ſuch things, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.30. The <hi>Lamb</hi> there <hi>Leads and feeds them,</hi> Rev. 7.16, 17, they are then clothed with Glory, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2, <hi>&amp;c,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">(2.) From Labours of <hi>Infirmity,</hi> they have their <hi>Writs of Eaſe.</hi> No <hi>more pain,</hi> as well as <hi>no more pains,</hi> Rev. 21.4. No <hi>Grief</hi> nor <hi>Gripes</hi> then, <hi>Job</hi> in no fear of the <hi>Caldeans</hi> there, <hi>Job</hi> 3.17, 18. Their <hi>Bacah</hi> is then turned into <hi>Berachah,</hi> their <hi>ſighing</hi> into <hi>ſinging, miſery</hi> into <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty: All Tears are wip'd from their Eyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">(3.) From the Labours of <hi>Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</hi> All men are under a Sinful Neceſſity here, <hi>Eccles.</hi> 7.20. Sin will keep houſe with us, whether
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:46511:41"/>we will or no: 'Tis an heart-greiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Inmate, till <hi>Death</hi> turn it out of doors, as <hi>Sarah</hi> did <hi>Hagar, Gen.</hi> 21.10. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This the Anti-Type Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pified by the <hi>fretting</hi> Leproſie, that could not be ſcraped out of the walls of the houſe infected with it until all the Stones and Timber thereof were taken down to the ground, <hi>Levit.</hi> 14.45, 44, 45. As <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltimus morborum medicus est mors,</hi> Death heals all the Diſeaſes of the Body. So <hi>Peccatum erat obſtetrix mortis, &amp; mors erit Sepulchrum peccati,</hi> Sin was the. Mid-wife to Death, and Death ſhall be the Sepulchre of Sin in the Soul. A believing Soul is not taken away <hi>in his ſins,</hi> (as <hi>John</hi> 8.21.) but <hi>from his ſins:</hi> Till then, we are all bound to this Body of Sin, which makes us cry out, [<hi>O Wretched men that wc are,</hi> &amp;c.] This brings down with Sorrow to the Grave. But then
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:46511:41"/>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> Delivers us from that Bond, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24, 25. Cauſing the Death of the Body, quite to deſtroy that <hi>Body of Death,</hi> till then, mans life is a <hi>ſore Travel,</hi> Eccles. 1.13. &amp; 2.23 While the Plummets of Sin hang at the heels of our Souls, we are <hi>Reſtleſs,</hi> altogether Reſtleſs, but when <hi>Death</hi> comes to Strike off thoſe Plummets, Then there is <hi>a Reſt in deed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Third and laſt Reſemblance in <hi>Job</hi> 9.26. is from the <hi>Eagles Fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> the <hi>Climax</hi> here is very obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, An <hi>Eagle</hi> is ſwifter than a Ship, as a Ship ſwifter than a <hi>Poſt.</hi> The <hi>Eagle,</hi> of all flying Fowls is reputed the ſwifteſt flight, and hath the ſtrongeſt Wing, <hi>Habb.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.19. The way of an <hi>Eagle</hi> in the Air, is <hi>High, Swift</hi> &amp; <hi>Strong.</hi> Thus Life haſteth from us, and Death
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:46511:42"/>haſtens to us, as doth the <hi>Eagle</hi> to the <hi>Carcaſs</hi> it deſireth to devour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.28. Then is the <hi>Eagle</hi> moſt ſwift when hunger (as it were) doth add Wings to his Wings, then comes he upon his Prey, like a Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-Bolt upon the Earth, ſwiftly and ſuddenly, before it can ſhift for it ſelf. Thus <hi>Death</hi> is not ſaid to walk on foot, but is mounted on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.8. <hi>Death rideth upon the Pale Horſe.</hi> Death Rideth <hi>Poſt</hi> (as above) upon a winged Horſe to us, as Life doth the like in <hi>Poſting</hi> from us. Oh how ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſome perſons are ſurprized with <hi>ſudden Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Sixth and laſt <hi>Obſervation</hi> is from the Quality of it, <hi>mans life is alſo a moſt miſerable Life.</hi> 'Tis not only a poor Pilgrimage, but 'tis alſo a ſhort and <hi>miſerable</hi> one: 'Tis called
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:46511:42"/>here a <hi>Pilgrimage,</hi> and that made up of a <hi>few</hi> daies, and thoſe <hi>evil</hi> ones al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. When <hi>Man</hi> came firſt out of <hi>Gods Mint,</hi> (in his ſtate of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency) he was a curious Silver-Peice, which ſhone moſt gloriouſly, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.5. <hi>Eccles.</hi> 7.29, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But now ſince the <hi>Fall,</hi> he is become a poor, thin, worn <hi>loſt Groat, Luke</hi> 15.8, 9. Which hath loſt its <hi>luſtre, weight,</hi> the <hi>ſound of ſilver,</hi> and its <hi>image</hi> and <hi>ſuperſcription:</hi> He is now the <hi>Prodigal</hi> loſt, and a Pilgrim wandering in the <hi>Wilderneſs of ſin,</hi> when caſt out of the <hi>Garden of God. Man</hi> is now become miſerable every way, miſerable in his Name, <hi>Enoſh,</hi> which ſignifies, <hi>(mere miſery.)</hi> And in his Nature, but a bagg of Dung, a lump, not only of <hi>Vanity,</hi> but of <hi>Miſery</hi> alſo. <hi>Man</hi> is miſerable,</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) At his Birth, <hi>Antequam na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt Damnatus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ambroſe;</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:46511:43"/>He is <hi>Condemned</hi> as he is <hi>Conceived:</hi> His <hi>Birth</hi> is polluted, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.5. and <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.4, 5. &amp; <hi>Job</hi> 14.12. He comes crying into the World, prophecying (as it were) that he is now launching out of the Haven of the Womb, into the wide Ocean of Care and Calamity: So,</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) He is miſerable <hi>in his Life:</hi> A Life <hi>Full of Trouble,</hi> Job 14.1. <hi>He is Born to miſery,</hi> Job 5.7. His <hi>Childhood</hi> and <hi>Youth</hi> is not only <hi>Vanity, Eccles.</hi> 11.10. But if not <hi>vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany,</hi> 'tis yet <hi>miſery.</hi> Yea his Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die-Age is made miſerable by graſp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too greedily of that bundle of Thorns, the <hi>World,</hi> &amp;c. Much more his Old-Age, which is expreſly called <hi>an Evil Age, Eccles.</hi> 12.1. Thus in theſe four reſpects, <hi>man</hi> is more than thrice miſerable as to <hi>his life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:46511:43"/>(3.) At his <hi>Death</hi> moſt of all, (if not Bornagain, before he Dye) then he doth but <hi>Begin his Endleſs Miſery.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE.</hi> I.</head>
               <p>Oh that I could be a <hi>Boanerges,</hi> or <hi>Son of Thunder,</hi> to awaken ſouls out of the <hi>fleep of Sin, [what meaneſt thou O thou Sleeper, ariſe?</hi> &amp;c. Jon. 1.6. <hi>Awake, awake, why ſleepeſt thou,</hi> &amp;c. Eph. 5.14. <hi>Call upon thy God,</hi> and be not ſtill faſt lull'd aſleeep, by a Soul-undoing Devil, in the bewitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Cradle of Carnal Security. Knoweſt thou not, that upon this <hi>moment</hi> (and God only knows how ſhort it may be) depends no leſs than thy <hi>Eternity</hi> of <hi>Woe</hi> or <hi>Weal?</hi> As the Tree falls, ſo it lyes, and ſo it riſes again: what way the Tree leans, that way it falls, either to <hi>South</hi> or <hi>North,</hi> and it leans that
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:46511:44"/>way it hath moſt boughs on; O then enquire, on what ſide moſt boughs grow, that to <hi>Heaven</hi> or that to <hi>Hell?</hi> Ye had better dye in a Ditch, Dunghil, or Dungeon, as <hi>Dye in ſin,</hi> Joh. 8.21.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE.</hi> II.</head>
               <p>Then Study this <hi>Patriarchs Opticks,</hi> who had a Right Proſpect of <hi>mans life;</hi> that it is but a <hi>Lingring Death,</hi> a <hi>Poor, Short</hi> and <hi>Miſerable Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage,</hi> wherein thou muſt expect <hi>foul way</hi> and <hi>weather,</hi> as well as <hi>fair:</hi> A <hi>Returna Brevi Term</hi> may (ere ever thou be aware) determine thy Pilgrimage. The <hi>Angels</hi> Queſtion to <hi>Hagar, [Whence comeſt thou, and whither goeſt thou?]</hi> Gen. 16.8. (Whether to <hi>Heaven,</hi> or <hi>Hell</hi>) is of Infinite Importance? <hi>He that gathers in</hi> Summer, <hi>is a wiſe ſon,</hi> Prov. 10.5
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:46511:44"/>As this <hi>Young-Man,</hi> (whoſe Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral we are Solemnizing) did: He had learnt to look upon all worldly things, with a <hi>Pilgrim's Eye,</hi> and to make uſe of them (in his way Home) with a <hi>Pilgrims Heart.</hi> Much more might I ſay, from my own perſonal Knowledge, were it not, that it is not my manner to <hi>Paint Sepulchres,</hi> or <hi>to Beautifie the Tombs of the dead,</hi> which is a work fitter for a <hi>Phariſee,</hi> Mat. 23.29. than for a Goſpel-Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE.</hi> III.</head>
               <p>Oh that all Young Men, were ſuch <hi>Mortified Timothies</hi> as <hi>He was,</hi> who lived much in a little Time! And though <hi>he be deprived of the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due of his dayes,</hi> Iſa, 38.10. And hath not the <hi>long life, promiſed to Piety,</hi> yet God keeps his Word with him,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:46511:45"/>for his Promiſe is but with the Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of this life, but his <hi>Payment</hi> is with the <hi>Gold of a Better</hi> Life. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> whom <hi>God Loves, Dye Young:</hi> He's taken <hi>away from the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil to come,</hi> 2 Kings 22.20. Iſa. 57.1. He hath lived long enough, that can ſay, (not, I have Married my Children to good Husbands, as Worldlings ſay, but) I have Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried my precious Soul, to the Bleſſed Bridegroom: This was his Joy, yet could be Content to paſs out of the midſt of this <hi>Joy on Earth,</hi> to poſſeſs a <hi>Better</hi> and <hi>Greater i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Heaven:</hi> And O that we may enter into our Maſters Joy, as he hath done! As a <hi>Poſt</hi> that hath delivered his Pacquet to God, a <hi>Ship</hi> that is laid up in the Haven of Heaven, &amp; an <hi>Eagle</hi> now feeding on the Car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>caſs of Chriſt</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:46511:45"/>
            <head>A Brief Relation of the <hi>Firſt Converſion</hi> and (after that) of the <hi>whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation</hi> of that precious Young Man Mr. <hi>John Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> drawn out of his <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences, Exerciſes, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminations</hi> of <hi>Himſelf,</hi> and his Evidences for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; all writ with his own hand in Characters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>HAving diligently peruſed what a prodigious account he gives of himſelf with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is own Hand-writing, I could
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:46511:46"/>not but ſtand aſtoniſhed, that one ſo young, and a ſervant too, and who had ſo much buſineſs on Earth in his Maſters ſervice, ſhould redeem ſo much time to make <hi>Religion his buſineſs,</hi> in ſerving his great Maſter Chriſt, and in ſecuring Heaven for his Soul: Though it ſeems almoſt incredible, yet it is moſt certainly true, that he Mellowed much, and Ripened faſt for <hi>Abrahams</hi> Boſom, as appears by the Sequel.</p>
               <p>This Holy Young Man may be a very eminent <hi>Patern of Piety</hi> to Old as well as Young Men, in a fourfold reſpect (1.) for his <hi>Experiences,</hi> (2.) for his <hi>Exerciſes,</hi> (3.) for his <hi>Self-Examinations,</hi> and (4.) for his <hi>Excellent Characters</hi> and <hi>Eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of his Intereſt in a better World. All which I find very ſtrenuouſly ſtated in his own Hand-writing, though in Characters, yet by the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:46511:46"/>help of a Key is made both legible and intelligible, and now publiſhed for publick good.</p>
               <p n="1">I. For his <hi>Experiences,</hi> they fall under a twofold head, the former relates to his firſt <hi>Converſion,</hi> and the latter to his whole <hi>Converſation:</hi> His <hi>Converſion</hi> (I underſtand) was effectually wrought (notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his ſtrict and Religious Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and former convictions hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mentioned, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) by a Sermon preached from Matth. 5.25, 26. [<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with thy Adverſary quickly while thou art in the way,</hi> &amp;c.] About <hi>December</hi> the 8th. 1678. From whence He learned thoſe bleſſed truths fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, and not only had them fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon his Heart, and ſealed upon his Soul, but alſo I find his own Soul fixed (in wax) upon them, to expreſs the great Veneration of them for their being ſo Raviſhing and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:46511:47"/>Refreſhing (in the Hand of <hi>Chriſt</hi>) to his Spirit. The Great Truths that had an abiding work upon his heart when this <hi>Time of Love</hi> came upon him, were theſe;</p>
               <p n="1">I. That God and Man are at va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance through ſin, they are at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
               <p n="2">II. 'Tis mans wiſdom to make his peace with God his <hi>Adverſary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. This muſt be done <hi>quickly,</hi> while <hi>Man is in his way,</hi> before he be brought to the <hi>Judges</hi> Houſe by death, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">IV. There is great danger in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laying or deferring this agreement, but ſinners ſhould take up with God before it be too late, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">V. That God hath an Action of Debt, for which to arreſt every ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">VI. This <hi>Debt of ſin</hi> is ſtrangely circumſtanced, (1.) 'tis an <hi>Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary,</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:46511:47"/>(2) an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> Debt; both every man is born in this Debt, and no man living is exempted from it. (3.) 'tis an increaſing and a grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing debt, the longer it runs on in a mans life, &amp;c. (4.) 'tis an infinite debt and therefore inſoluble; it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be paid <hi>&amp;c.</hi> no finite creature can ever pay this infinite debt, to the infinite Creator. Thoſe bleſſed truths the Lord ſpake <hi>with a ſtrong hand</hi> (as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.11.) to this <hi>Young Mans heart,</hi> and made him conſider,</p>
               <p>Firſt, That till this Agreement be made, my God is my Adverſary, and I had better have all the World my Enemy, the Maker of the World, who, if a friend can make my Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Friends, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, I cannot ſtand it out with the great God, who will burn up thoſe bryars that ſet themſelves againſt him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.4.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:46511:48"/>Thirdly, 'Tis no frivolous thing to be done or undone, but 'tis a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of great moment; Eternal weal and woe hangs upon it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, I muſt agree, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> becauſe there is no other way in all the World to take up this prodigious debt but by agreement, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, It will not always be my priviledge to make an agreement; Time will not laſt always for taking up the Controverſy, for when Death comes, then it is to late, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly, If my cauſe come before the Righteous Judge, I am ſure to be caſt, becauſe 'tis a bad cauſe, and that Judge will not be bribed with any thing in the day of Judgment.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, It I be caſt in my cauſe, I ſhall be delivered up by the Judge to Gods Gaoler and Executioner, to wit, the Devil.</p>
               <p>Eightly, If I be Delivered over to
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:46511:48"/>Gods officer of Juſtice, he will caſt me into Priſon, that is, Dragg me into hell.</p>
               <p>Ninthly, If once I be caſt into the priſon of Hell; there muſt I lye, till I have paid the uttermoſt Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, which can never be done, I muſt be always paying the Debt, yet never have paid it.</p>
               <p>By theſe Soul-awaking Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the Lord help'd him (through his Grace) to conclude with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, That it was the higheſt Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in the World to agree quickly with God his Adverſary (as he was a <hi>child of Wrath by nature,</hi> Eph. 2.3.) and it would be the moſt ſublime Folly for him any longer to deferr it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon the Lord having thus opened his Eyes, touch'd his Heart and broke down windows into his Dark Soul, upon further inquiry he
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:46511:49"/>learned, that this vaſt debt he was owing to Divine Juſtice (no leſs than <hi>Ten thouſand Talents,</hi> Mat. 18.24. which is no leſs than a Kings Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom) could never be compounded for: This juſt Judge will have either All or None, and till an Agreement be made, God is an angry Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary: And better I ſhould anger all the Witches in the World, and all the Devils in Hell, than anger the great God, <hi>I muſt agree with Him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then the inquiry was made how this might be done?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The anſwer was, there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing lays on Gods part, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing on yours: That on <hi>Gods part</hi> is (1.) to find an Arbitrator or <hi>Days-Man</hi> one more than a man, for what could a meer man do with an angry God? (2.) God <hi>found a Ranſom,</hi> a
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:46511:49"/>
                  <hi>Surety</hi> to <hi>ſatisfy the debt</hi> with the <hi>Travel of his Soul. Job</hi> 33.24. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.22. and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.11. (3.) God makes the Sinners Heart wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing to accept of this way of Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Phil</hi> 2.13. That which <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ays on mans part</hi> is two fold, (1.) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <hi>let go ſin</hi> (not only in action but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n affection alſo) and (2.) to <hi>lay hold on Chriſt</hi> as one undone without Him: Thus came this bleſſed Soul to be <hi>broken off from the Wild Olive, Rom.</hi> 11.24. In his letting go and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aying down of ſin, as the greateſt evil, and by Grace became grafted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto that Bleſſed and Bleeding Vine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he <hi>Lord Jeſus, John</hi> 15.1, 2. who ever after his happy grafting time, became a fruit bearing branch, have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng juice and nouriſhment admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred abundantly to him from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ree of Life Jeſus Chriſt, as the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel will manifeſt in almoſt unparal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eld inſtances.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:46511:50"/>Thus far in ſhort, for his experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences in his <hi>firſt Converſion,</hi> now come we to treat more largely of his <hi>whole Converſation,</hi> ſome parts whereo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall be reduced to the three follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Heads, His <hi>Exerciſes:</hi> His <hi>Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations</hi> of Himſelf, and his <hi>Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences</hi> for Heaven which he attain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> unto, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>NOW after his thorough a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſound <hi>Converſion</hi> follows <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> holy <hi>Converſation,</hi> which appear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to be much in Heaven by his conve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſing ſo much with God, and with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> own heart, in his due preparatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for, and true participation of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> greateſt of ordinances, the <hi>Lords S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:46511:50"/>as is manifeſt by thoſe experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences writ with his own hand upon that ſubject which with no ſmall trouble yet with great delight are here tranſcribed.</p>
               <p>Now that he was <hi>bred</hi> and made a new creature by his <hi>effectual calling</hi> he found and felt a neceſſity that he muſt alſo be fed, ſo asks councel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the concern of his Soul, and learnt thoſe Divine Leſſons which He recorded.</p>
               <p>As (1.) the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> is ſo called becauſe our <hi>Lord</hi> ordained it at his laſt <hi>Supper</hi> inſtead of the <hi>Paſſover.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">(2.) 'tis the duty of Beleivers to receive it, elſe they do ſlight his Love, and diſobey his Command.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) And to receive it often ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Chriſts command and the Apoſtles practice.</p>
               <p n="4">(4.) That being dull and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under my Spiritual wants (ſaith
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:46511:51"/>he) I muſt give all dilligence topre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare my Heart for ſo great a work: All are naturally unfit, God will come and veiw his gueſts, I have to do with the Son of God, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="5">(5.) This preparation muſt be made by a narrow ſearch of my own Heart concerning my <hi>Sins,</hi> my <hi>wants</hi> and my <hi>Graces,</hi> and by fervent and ſolemn prayer.</p>
               <p n="6">(6.) The Graces I muſt go to God and get from him are, <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Faith, Love, Repentance,</hi> and <hi>New Obedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">(7.) I muſt have <hi>Knowledg,</hi> for without it the heart cannot be good, nor can I know my ſelf nor diſcern the <hi>Lords Body:</hi> I muſt know how man was created, and how he fell and I in him, how we are recovered by Chriſt, how renewed after the image of God in knowledg, &amp;c. till then my underſtanding is dark
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:46511:51"/>and ignorant, my conſcience benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, my affections out of order and ſet upon wrong objects, my memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry brittle, my eyes full of adultry and my whole Frame out of Frame, the knowledg of thoſe things will help to break my heart that ſuch a filthy lump of Sin as I am, ſhould ſee and feel the arms of Chriſt imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing me.</p>
               <p n="8">(8.) I muſt have <hi>Faith</hi> whereby I may hartily receive him as my Lord and Redeemer, and rely upon him alone both for ſafety and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Without <hi>faith 'tis not poſſible to pleaſe God,</hi> and I may not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe him at his own Table, when I go thither for the food of my Soul.</p>
               <p n="9">(9.) I muſt have repentance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I muſt judg my ſelf, that I be not judged: I muſt both mourn for ſin and turn from ſin, when I come to the Lords Table, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:46511:52"/>(10.) I muſt have <hi>Love</hi> too, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Apoſtle ſaith <hi>[without Love all is nothing]</hi> 'tis uncomfortable to ſit down at the table of an enemy (whom we love not, and who loves not us) but 'tis dreadfull and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to ſit down in our Enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p n="11">(11.) I muſt have new <hi>Obedience</hi> alſo, elſe I come in my rebellion, and for Some Siniſter end, not out of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. I muſt here renew my co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God, and be as ſerious as if I were to dye: Both in begging to be rid of that Sin which moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbs the peace of my Soul and to have that mercy which would do me moſt good in a Dying Hour, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="12">(12.) I muſt quicken and draw forth into act all theſe forenamed <hi>Habits</hi> of Grace when I come to the Lords Table, there meditating upon
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:46511:52"/>the great work of mans redemption, Gods ſeverity againſt ſin in the death of my Surety &amp; Savior, the preciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my Soul, that coſt ſuch a price and the priviledges purchaſed for me thereby, for which I muſt be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Having thus ſolemnly prepared his Soul for this great and tremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous ordinance from <hi>July</hi> 22. 1681. to <hi>Auguſt</hi> the <hi>7h.</hi> before he was yet twenty years old he ſat down the firſt time upon that day at the <hi>Lords Table:</hi>—Upon this <hi>firſt Sacrament,</hi> he received <hi>Auguſt</hi> the ſeventh, thus he writes, Before I ſat down, and at my firſt approach to the Table, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Fear and Trembling ſeized upon me, but ſoon after I had ſome Sweet Sights of my Dear <hi>Redeemer:</hi> I ſaw him by Faith, how he ſtood with his Arms wide open to receive me, and how he was Pierced, that
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:46511:53"/>the Blood came out of his Bleſſed and Bleeding Sides: I had then a clearer Sight of my God (through my Redeemer) and of his bleſſed Angels. This was raviſhing, and Oh how refreſhing; but could not get my heart Inflamed enough with Love to Chriſt. I laid open my Sins and beg'd the Pardon of them might be Sealed. I promiſed to live up to this Obligation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning the <hi>Second Sacrament</hi> he Received <hi>Sept.</hi> 4. 1681. He gives this account. [I had not duely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared my Heart for ſo great a work and Ordinanance, but bleſſed for ever, bleſſed be the Lord, who did not deal with me according to my unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paredneſs, which if he had done, I had not been here, but been baniſhed from his preſence, and ſo been under the Death of Deaths. But he was pleaſed to give me a Sight of himſelf
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:46511:53"/>(which I eſteem above life) and likewiſe a Sight of God and Chriſts conferring about mans Redemption. I ſaw the Lord (as it were) ſaying, Come ye Holy Angels, behold man is fallen, ſee if ye can find a way for his recovery, which they could not, but Chriſt took upon him mans ſalvation: And I ſaw my ſelf (as it were) in Hell where I had for ever laid, but Chriſt came, and drew me out, then I embraced him as my <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, Prieſt</hi> and <hi>King,</hi> and became willing to forſake the World and all for Chriſt: O that I may do it more and more, and never have this frame worn off, but that while I am be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low with my Body, my Soul may be above with my God, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Third Sacrament</hi> was <hi>October</hi> 2d. 1681. on which he writes thus as the miniſter (in adminiſtring) was ſaying. So that you are unfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:46511:54"/>willing to receive Chriſt, and whom nothing will ſatisfy but him, I bid come and welcome to take him, then were my thoughts fixed upon Chriſt, though they had been wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring two days before, and I had loſt my beloved, yet nothing could give me peace till I here found Him, and Sweet communion with Him, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I heard him ſay to my Soul, thy ſins (ſmal and great) are pardoned, and thy pardon is ſealed; I ſaw (as it were) his precious blood ſpurting out of his ſides into my heart. Oh my Soul ever for ever love this Love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Lord, admire and adore him who hath ſealed thy pardon: Never ſin more, but walk ſuitably to all this &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Fourth Sacrament</hi> was <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> 6. 1681 whereof he ſaith thus, I have longed for this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, becauſe I had more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:46511:54"/>ſins (ſuch as <hi>pride</hi> that I had long groaned under) which made me long for the ſprinkling of my Dear Redeemers blood to waſh them away. I was alſo peſtered with <hi>paſſion</hi> (as well as pride) with <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief,</hi> with wandring <hi>thoughts</hi> and ſome times with <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> (O cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, curſed ſin, and O wicked wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed heart, once to think whether God was or no, when thou haſt had ſuch clear evidences of a Diety) theſe were my five deadly odious ſins, which I begg'd might be purged from me.</p>
               <p>O that I may never ſee nor feel them more: At this Ordinance, I found relief, and feeling the Wine falling down lower and lower, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired it might carry of all my filth, ſo as to leave none remaining, and there did I reſolve (through grace) to leave thoſe five ſins, and never
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:46511:55"/>have any thing to do with them &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Fifth Sacrament</hi> was <hi>December</hi> 4. 1681. wherein (ſaith he) I did again lay my ſins before the Lord fearing their return upon me, did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a meek and humble heart againſt my <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>paſſion;</hi> I did again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign my ſelf to God, having broken Covenant with Him, and begging (with the <hi>Syrophaenician</hi> Woman) to touch the Hem of Chriſts gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that I might be cleanſed from my iſſue of ſin, but could not at that inſtant get ſo nigh him but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards had I a clear repreſentation of Chriſts ſufferings in the Garden where he bore the wrath of God, ſweating drops of blood, through his cloths in a cold ſeaſon, ſo that he came as from <hi>Bozra,</hi> with died gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, then I ſaw the crown of thorns upon his head and his head
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:46511:55"/>beaten with the Soldiers iron-gloves which made the thorns wound his Holy Head in 72. places, ſo that the blood ran down upon his body, I ſaw alſo the heavy weight of the croſs laid upon Him, and how he was ſpit upon, reviled and derided; this bleſſed ſight prevented wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring thoughts, till the laſt prayer, though I did not deſerve the leaſt crumb of comfort for unpreparedneſs to ſo great a work, which, had God dealt out my deſert, would have been no leſs than Hell, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sixth Sacrament</hi> he did par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of was <hi>January</hi> the firſt 1681/2. upon which he makes theſe remarks, I had been ſome days before more than ordinary in my preparation and prayer for a profitable receiving, and when I came to it, I was ſore afraid that I ſhould lay ſtreſs upon preparatory actings, therfore beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:46511:56"/>I of God that he would not deal with me accordingly, I laboured to act my requiſite graces.</p>
               <p>As (1.) <hi>Repentance</hi> laying open before the Lord all my old year ſins to that New-years day and laboured to mourn for them more than for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, eſpecially for my deadly dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſins, <hi>Spiritual pride, Paſſionateneſs, Wandring Thoughts</hi> in Holy Duties, <hi>unbeleif, worldlineſs</hi> &amp;c. and I hope God gave there both pardon of them and power againſt them.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) My thankfulneſs I actuated (as well as I could) for ſo rich a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, begging for it both hard and always.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) My love, though I had much too little, experiencing the ſweet Kiſſes of Chriſts mouth, and Embraces of his love, I ſaw Chriſt on the Croſs Embracing me as vvell as I him, and ſaying to God [I have
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:46511:56"/>paid a Ranſom for him, this man is he, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] This was ſo ſweet, that I could embrace the ſtake or even go into hell, ſo I might thus enjoy him whom my Soul loved; and when I heard the Miniſter ſay, mourn for your ſins that murdred your Lord, I anſwered within my ſelf, <hi>How can the Children of the Bride mourn while the Bridegroom is with them?</hi> Twice did wandring thoughts offer themſelves but were (by grace) ſuppreſſed at the firſt riſing, having now obliged my underſtanding, will, memory, affections, conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, yea all to attend Gods ſervice: While thus fill'd with this enjoyment I longed to be in Heaven, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that welcom, welcom friend death that I might ſing with the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Saints and Angels Hallelujahs to to the Lord: then ſaid I, O my Soul let nothing draw thy love from thy Lord: For the World, Friends, Relations, Pleaſures, Profits, all things
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:46511:57"/>put together, can never give ſuch joy to thee as thou haſt found from lovely, lovely Jeſus in this bleſſed ordinance, therefore lay not out thy love upon any thing beſides Him, who hath done and is doing great things, yea and will do greater for thee. Such was my warming war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming loves at this Supper.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Seventh Sacrament</hi> was <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary</hi> the 3. 1681/2. Upon which he remarks thus, [when I found my heart not fully fixed by my New years Day Sacrament, but notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all my ſtriving I was yet trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with diſtraction in duty, I long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for this ordinance very much and thought it long till it came that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts might be made even between God and my poor Soul. I was dull for 2. or 3. Duties before and could not get my heart raiſed, whereby I ſaw that I deſerved nothing: though wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring thoughts preſſed upon me, yet were they cut ſhort 2 or 3 times,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:46511:57"/>&amp; I found relief from thoſe ſins I had laid open before the Lord in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Sacrament. I bewailed my breaking covenant, my diſtraction, my deadneſs and coldneſs in duty, &amp;c. And at this Sacrament my Dear Redeemer met me &amp; ſaid to me I have pardoned thoſe thy ſins at thy requeſt, this much affected and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livened me in love to him, ſeeing him then as (it were) coming from Heaven to the Earth, and from Earth to the Croſs (ſhedding his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood for me) and from the Croſs into Glory; and (methought) Chriſt ſaid to me, go ſin theſe your ſins no more, which obliged me to a cloſe walking and to be more watchful than before; all this month the Lord kept me from <hi>pride,</hi> but alas my other ſins returned to foil me.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Eighth Sacrament</hi> was <hi>March</hi> 5. 1681/2. Upon this he ſaith thus: I had more than ordinary commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:46511:58"/>with God before it, and have not had a ſweeter ſeaſon for a long time, which made me long till it came; in this ordinance, I ſaw my dear Redeemer (as it were) dead with a company of Holy Angels hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Him and a great darkneſs over all the place, this was grief to my Soul, but preſently he that was dead I ſaw him alive again and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into the midſt of us to ſee what we came for, I went to him and told him (methought) that my Soul loved him, and I was come to meet him for ſtrength againſt corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and by his help I could forſake the world and ſin (which I hated) to enjoy him, &amp;c. then he told me, my <hi>pride</hi> ſhould not prevail againſt me this month, nor my other ſins but by own neglect. This was ſweet and refreſhing to my Soul, and this was the occaſion of the Devils great rage againſt me (as appears by my Diary <hi>March</hi> 14.) yet could
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:46511:58"/>he not prevail, but Chriſt kept his promiſe in keeping me from <hi>pride,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Oh what cauſe have I to love the Lord Jeſus, whom I ſaw here again coming from Heaven to Earth, to the Croſs to the Grave and to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven again, and all this to ſave my Soul, here ſin was made more odious Chriſt more dear, and here I renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my Covenant with God, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> Ninth Sacrament <hi>was</hi> April <hi>the</hi> 2d. 1682. <hi>upon which he ſays thus, Some Time before this I was in a dull frame by the hurries of our Trade, at this time (as may be ſeen by my diary) little life could I find till the noon before that day, then had I the preſence of my Dear Lord in a lively manner and meaſure, after this wandring thoughts dulneſs and coldneſs (unſuitable to ſo ſweet a ſupper) ſeized upon me, but by running over again the ſame circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of my Saviours ſufferings, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially his Agony in the Garden and all
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:46511:59"/>for ſuch a wretch as me, I found relief, got hatred of my ſins, begged pardon of them: And not only ſo but got power againſt them; yet wandring thoughts</hi> 4 <hi>or</hi> 5 <hi>times did trouble me, but by Chriſts strengthening me I overcame them, and hoped to have my pardon ſealed; and to have power for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for watching better againſt them and againſt my deadneſs and breaking my Covenant, &amp;c. which made me long to quit the World whereupon it was anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wered me, I ſhould ſhortly be freed from all ſin, yet in this Sacrament I had the leaſt communion with God than in any before but ſtill much more, infinitely more than I deſerved, who (ſure I am) deſerves not the leaſt mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Tenth Sacrament</hi> was <hi>May</hi> 7. 1682. <hi>upon which he writes thus,</hi> I had not longing deſires after this Bleſſed Ordinance, having loſt much of my life I had in duty before through much hurries of our worldly affairs: This morning I wreſtled
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:46511:59"/>with God, but had not the light of his countenance which made me think of not going, yet conſidering that was not the way to be better I ventured, but found no life at firſt, yet a little after I felt ſome reaching after my Dear Redemer, this made me reſolve to walk more cloſely for the future, after this it pleaſed God to come in (out of his free love) and to give me a clear ſight of my ſweet Saviours going to his Croſs, and I fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing him and laying my ſelf down at his feet, when I could do nothing; Then had I plain viſions of my love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Lords aſcenſions and his Angels looking upon him, whereat I found much goings out of my Soul, after him, yet wandring thoughts did trouble me for I had not brought my breaking Covenant, my Dulneſs and Deadneſs before the Lord, ſo as to be deeply humbled for them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> Eleventh Sacrament <hi>was</hi> June 4, 1682. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon which he He remarks,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:46511:60"/>thus, I having no time, was very bad in my preparations for this bleſſed Sacrament, ſo doubted whether I ſhould go to it, but fearing it might be the laſt I ſhould injoy in peace I then went, yet it prov'd the worſt I ever yet had, I hardly felt any movings of affections only a little mourning for my breach of Covenant, my coldneſs and deadneſs, &amp;c. Had a little ſight of my Deareſt Redeemer, but O my miſery for not keeping my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement made in the foregoing Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: whereby I feared the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit was greived and ſinned away, O ſad ſad, lamentable, deplorable was my state when I had ſinned my God from me: My condition was wretched now and without more care it may yet be much worſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> Twelfth Sacrament <hi>was on</hi> July 2d. 1682. <hi>whereupon he notes thus, I was but little in preparation in order to my participation of this Holy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, yet much more than on the laſt; on Fryday morning before I had much
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:46511:60"/>of Gods preſence, but becauſe I had not taken a Catalogue of my ſins, and had broke my vows with God, 'tis juſt with him to hide his face from me, and O my deadly ſin got again too much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage againſt me, yet praiſed be the free Grace of my God, I had his preſence in this Ordinance, and ſaw my Dear Redeemer going along bearing his heavy Croſs, and his ſuffering thereupon and when his ſide was pierced, (me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought) I ſtood under, and his precious blood did drop down upon me; but ſtill I was too little grieved for ſin, and had 3. times wandrings which (through Grace) paſſed away, as the Wine went down I deſired my ſins might be purged away and renewed my reſolve of walking better, both before and in this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, deſigning to ſhelter my Soul in the holes of his bleſſed Side (that was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ierced) as the</hi> Dove <hi>doth in the holes of the Rock.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> Thirteenth Sacrament <hi>was</hi> Auguſt 6. 1682. <hi>On which he records
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:46511:61"/>thus: The hurries of the World had made menegligent before it, yet did I try my ſelf by my catalogue of ſins drawn up in</hi> Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary <hi>before, ſuch as</hi> pride (<hi>whereof I had a great deal</hi>) breach of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant (<hi>whereof I was greatly guilty)</hi> Wandrings, Dullneſs in Duty, <hi>&amp;c. and then another great one the neglect of</hi> ſelf tryal <hi>after my vows &amp; renewed Covenant to do it, after Sacraments, wherein I had found much ſweetneſs: I could not ſtill call my ſelf to a ſtrict account, nor actuate my repentance as becomes a worthy receiver though my ſins were many and great: At my firſt ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting down, I had but little ſenſe of ſin, but after God ſhowed me ſomething of himſelf, then had I ſome ſorrow of Soul and ſomething of my dear Lord, but once God ſeemed to come out in fury towards me, yet (methought) I ſaw my Dear Redeemer ſtop it: Here again I lay under the Croſs to be waſhed from my ſins and did ſee (as before) Chriſt coming from Heaven to Earth, to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:46511:61"/>Croſs and to his Grave and from thence into Glory, this I viewed with a little (oh too little) life, then the Devil tempted me to make no new engagement of reformation, but the Lord helped me, and I harkned not to the Tempter. About</hi> 4. <hi>times wandrings came, but (through grace) they continued not, yet had I ſmal actings of love and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goings of Soul after my God and my Dear Redeemer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> Fourteenth Sacrament <hi>was</hi> September 3. 1682. <hi>On which he obſerves thus, I had but little of God, ſome time before this till</hi> Saturday <hi>night. Though I had been much in preparation, yet my God came not in till then, and indeed I ſaw much ſin in my beſt ſervices, ſo begged God would not deal with me as I deſerved, which would have been hell and destruction: But comming to partake I had great hopes of his preſence, ſo ſoon as I had pleaded with God my laſt years ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then found I ſome revivings,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:46511:62"/>and hearing the two great points of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> (that God would be our God, &amp; we ſhould be his people) <hi>opened, then did I reſign up my ſelf to God with a more than ordinary reſignation. My end in coming to this Ordinance was to ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the partition wall (betwixt me &amp; my God) caſt down which I hope was attained, my</hi> Pride <hi>and other ſins were pardoned, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided I did not run into them again; I clove cloſe to Chriſt and would not let him go without his bleſſing, which my dear Redeemer gave me, though Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan preſented many things to prevent me thereof: The Lord ſaid here to me I will he thy God, and my Soul ſaid, I do ingage to he one of thy People, leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all that comes in competition with my ſweet Saviour,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> Fifteenth Sacrament <hi>was</hi> Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tober 5. 1682. he begins thus, <hi>Bleſſing, Praiſe, and Honour be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed unto my God, and Redeemer, who hath neither forgotten nor forſaken me, though I did deſerve it and Gods
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:46511:62"/>wrath too, for my manifold ſins, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of</hi> murmuring <hi>in ſome meaſure (I am afraid) is one, &amp;</hi> ſeeking praiſe among men <hi>is another: Though ſenſe of ſin had too little been upon my heart this laſt month, yet now was it more than uſual, but leſs than my ſins required, I pleaded with God that he commanded me to believe, to this I had great comfort returned and after much ſtrugling the Lord aſſured me my ſins were pardoned; then had I ſuch repreſentations of my Redeemer as I had oft before, when Gods juſtice impleaded me for my ſins, my ſweet Saviour did then anſwer, I have dyed and ſatisfied for him, at this the Devil envyed, telling me all this was but a fable, and would have diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me but (by grace) I overcame him: O how am I obliged to love God who hath given me ſmiles when I deſerved nothing but frowns, ſhall not I be more careful to pleaſe him, and more fearful to offend him (He ends as he began) Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, Praiſe, and Honour, be to my
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:46511:63"/>God and my Redeemer for ever,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> Sixteenth Sacrament <hi>was</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember 5. 1682. <hi>on which he ſaid thus, I have broke my covenant with God for the laſt month, by falling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe ſins I ingaged and reſolved againſt before, dulneſs in duty and diſtraction returned upon me having not ſtriven ſo much againſt them as I ſhould, and having little communion with God my deadly ſin prevailed, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nothing but fearful looking for of judgment was before me, being remiſs in my preparations yet God dealt not with me according to my deſerts, for then had I been ſet up as a monument of Divine Diſpleaſure among men: But before I ſat down I ſtrove to raiſe my repentance, yet could not mourn as my caſe required. I pleaded Gods promiſe, that his Son was ſent to ſave ſuch as I am, &amp;c. I ran over Chriſts ſufferings in my mind particularly, and ſeated my Soul at the feet of my bleeding Saviour on the Croſs that his precious
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:46511:63"/>blood might cleanſe away all my loads of ſins, I did juſtify God in all his dealing with me, and his withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from me, then did I receive Chriſt as my King, reſolving to forſake all for him and to follow him through all: ſome wandrings troubled me in Chriſts Wine-cellar but were ſoon cut off, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the <hi>Sacrament in December,</hi> he acknowledges his Omiſſion of it, by his own Negligence and Folly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> Seventeenth Sacrament <hi>was on</hi> January 7. 1681/3. <hi>where he writes thus; I did endeavour to prepare (yet but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>little, for this great Ordinance and could not for a long time get my affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons inflamed (as formerly) with love to the Lord Jeſus, however I caſt my ſins at his feet, to be waſhed away that the difference might be taken up and God might reconciled to my poor Soul again, which (bleſſed be the Lord) was hopefully accompliſhed: I did bewail my fearfull breaking covenant, the return
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:46511:64"/>of my multitude of ſins, eſpecially my deadly ſin</hi> pride: <hi>I again viewed over diſtinctly the ſufferings of Chriſt, how he was ſcourged, &amp;c. and all for poor me, this ſet me upon mourning, but I could not ſhed tears, yet complained of the hardneſs of my heart; and begg'd that Chriſts Precious Blood might both ſoften and cleanſe it, then (me thought) I ſaw Chriſt upon the Croſs ſtooping to me and giving me his hand, when he ſaw I could not get up my heart to him: Hereupon I claſped about my</hi> Dear Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer <hi>who had reconciled God to me, then I reſolved (in his ſtrength) never to fin in the like manner any more, and was angry with my ſelf for dealing ſo unkindly with ſo kind a Father, who had rather a ſinner ſhould repent than dye, God was loving to me who could, look for nothing but fury in the higheſt meaſure for my back-ſlidings; my heart would have wandred but (by Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) thoſe wandrings were taken ſhort: I here ſolemnly engaged to walk more
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:46511:64"/>cloſely with God for the future all my ſays, which if I did not, O how great will be my ſin, how vaſt will be my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs, beyond what my Tongue can expreſs.</hi>]</p>
               <p>Upon the whole, As our Lord ſaid of the <hi>Good Centurion</hi> [I have not found ſo great faith no not in all <hi>Iſrael.</hi>] ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m I like to ſay of this gracious Young-Man, I have not found ſuch ſavoury Soul-experiences on record <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o not in all <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This will further more fully appear by the ſequel in his Exerciſes, Self Examinations and Evidences.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>AFter his <hi>Experiences,</hi> come in the ſecond place his <hi>Exerciſes</hi> which are twofold, firſt concerning <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iety,</hi> ſecondly concerning <hi>impiety,</hi>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:46511:65"/>both before his effectual vocation and after it: Thoſe before he took with his own hand theſe memorials following.</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) About the year 1671. hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing read <hi>Jehoſephats</hi> life, I was a little ſtartled, and grew melancholick, that was the firſt time I had a mind to pray, and deſired another to joyn with me in it, but he told me that he could not pray without help of ſome form; no more (I ſaid) can I, but uſed a form in a ſpelling book, which I prayed often but very negligently, then going to <hi>Epſon,</hi> where I had a good maſter who prayed morning and evening with his family and religiouſly inſtructed us, which did bring me to pray without a form, yet could not d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it with ſeriouſneſs, tho' I was exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to it both by my maſter and by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> miniſter that came oft thither. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this place I began to be willing to hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Word, though I little minde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:46511:65"/>what I heard, till I read the <hi>Pilgrims Progreſs,</hi> which made me again grow melancholick (the former being worn off) to the obſervation of others; then the good providence of God brought to my hands Mr. <hi>Baxters Call to the unconverted,</hi> which (through grace,) ſhewed me the neceſſity of my converſion; yet all this time never conſulted with any man about my ſins, but only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed them to God, till I met with Mr. <hi>Hookers Soul preparation for Chriſt,</hi> which convinced me to adviſe with ſome Godly miniſter, hereupon I did addreſs to one though a ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to him, ſaying, Sir, I cannot, I dare not any longer refrain, having ask'd my ſelf what fitneſs I had to dye, was anſwered, I was unfit till I had eas'd my heart to you, as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) When I was 7. years old, I tore my Bible, and caſt away my Catechiſm.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:46511:66"/>(2.) I have broke the Sabbath, by rambling abroad, playing at far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things with naughty boys and waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf in the fields when I ſhould have been at the Church, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) By excuſing my ſins with a lye, ſo added one ſin to another, for covering it.</p>
               <p n="4">(4.) Nor have I been free from <hi>Youthful Luſts,</hi> which young <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> was bid to flee, but my corrupt Heart hath had workings after the Act, ſeveral times, yet hath been wonderfully prevented by the advice of my Godly Siſter, who laid before me Chriſts words, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.28. <hi>who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever looks on a woman to luſt after her,</hi> &amp;c. however, I am guilty of <hi>Heart-Adultry.</hi> yea,</p>
               <p n="5">(5.) I have, erred and laughed when I have heard the word preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with power, &amp;c. Hereupon the Good Miniſter gave me grave coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil and comfort ſuitable to my peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:46511:66"/>caſe and condition, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaning all this, I was not effectually called, nor througly converted, and made a new creature, until after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards I heard that Sermon upon <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.25, 26. as the account a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove mentioned ſpecifieth.</p>
               <p>But alas in my Apprentiſhip through the hurries of the World in our way of trading (eſpecially in <hi>May</hi> and <hi>June,</hi> &amp;c.) I became neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent of my cloſe walking with God, not minding (as I might) to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in his love, when God (my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary) was reconciled to me; I neglected Dayly, Self-examination, or did it only to halfe part, being dull and ſleepy through wearineſs with worldly work at night then my old corruptions got head again up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, I broke my Covenant made at the agreement with my adverſary and I Apoſtatized from theſe ſweet thoughts I formerly had upon my God and Dear Redeemer, for which
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:46511:67"/>(had he not been gracious) I had been damned and rotting in Hell for ever. This conſideration made me exclaim againſt my ſelf ſaying, O ſilly Soul to heed a periſhing dying world before Heaven, ſuch ſadneſs and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſeized on me at this time (when the things of the world, I found had been the ſubſtance of my thoughts and diſcourſe) that I knew not what to do, nor whither to go, at laſt I turned to the Lord and begged of him that he would not take the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture, nor ſuffer me to run this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy way to utter deſtruction.</p>
               <p>I cryed Lord, 'tis juſt with thee to hurle mein to hell and into the hotteſt place thereof, and never wait long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er upon ſuch a cumber-ground as I am: but to thee my Dear Redeemer do I run for refuge, as one that am hungry and hardly beſtead, poor, blind, naked, wretched and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, a loathſom wretch, unworthy to be called a ſervant, much leſs a
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:46511:67"/>Son, having ſo wickedly departed from my God, yet through thee will I venter again to my God, and by thy ſtrength I will better mind my future walkings: O my deareſt Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer I die without thee, O come in once again and let me feel once more what it is to have Chriſt dwelling in my Soul! O find a time of love wherein to diſperſe thoſe dark clouds and ſhine upon my Dead and Darkned Soul! O hath my night no day, 'tis an hell to me to be thruſt away from God, I know the cauſe is all at home, my ſin, my ſin, O let it be done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, then ſhould I recover the light of thy countenance as formerly, and in ſo doing I do ingage to amend my manners (depending on thy help) my hand is witneſs, <hi>John Draper.</hi> now to bind his Soul and Slippery heart to God the better in obſerving this new ingagement, he wrote down many profitable rules in his pocket book.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:46511:68"/>As (1.) In a day of humiliation I muſt lay all my ſins before the Lord and reſolve to forſake them.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) I muſt look upon my ſin of <hi>Paſſion</hi> as a feaver in my mind, of <hi>Lust,</hi> as fire in my bones, of <hi>Pride</hi> as a fatal tympany in my Soul, of covetouſneſs as an inſatiable and unſufferable thirſt, and the ſin of <hi>Envy</hi> or <hi>Malice</hi> as rank poyſon in the heart.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) If I would run ſo as to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain I muſt caſt off all thoſe weights or ſins that do ſo eaſily beſet me.</p>
               <p n="4">(4.) I muſt reſolve to begin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the running of this race.</p>
               <p n="5">(5.) Nor muſt I loyter in the way.</p>
               <p n="6">(6.) Nor muſt I cumber my ſelf with the needleſs incumbrances of the World.</p>
               <p n="7">(7.) I muſt look to every part of my way with equal care and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
               <p n="8">(8.) Nor muſt I ever think I
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:46511:68"/>have gone far enough till I have obtained the prize.</p>
               <p n="9">(9.) And the further I have run in this race, the more eager ſhould be to obtain the end.</p>
               <p n="10">(10.) I muſt alway think that I am upon the brink of eternity, and therefore ſhould give all diligence to make my calling and election ſure, working out my Salvation and making ſure work for a better world, before I go hence to be ſeen no more.</p>
               <p n="11">(11.) I muſt ever come to God as to a Soul-pittying, a Sin-pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and a Prayer-hearing God.</p>
               <p n="12">(12.) I muſt be fervent in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, yet ſubmit to Gods Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y.</p>
               <p n="13">(13.) Occaſions of being too <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ong alone, are to be avoided, ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Strong Drink, and too full a Dyet.</p>
               <p n="14">(14.) I muſt be thinking oft Death Judgment, Hell and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en, thoſe four laſt things</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:46511:69"/>(15.) I muſt not ſtretch my Chriſtian liberty too far, for he that dare go ſo far as he thinks he may, goes ſometime farther than he ſhould, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="16">(16.) I muſt bridle my Tongue and not be too apt to ſpeak of things whereof I am not certain: And much more to the ſame purpoſe both for particular and general inſtruction too long to inſert here.</p>
               <p>This Holy Young-Man put down in his pocket book alſo, how he had been <hi>Exerciſed</hi> with <hi>Temptations</hi> to Sin, as to Theft, Adultry, Playing at Cards, and prophaning the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, &amp;c. as alſo with tryals to prevent temptations, inſtancing that in a laſh upon his eye with a Coach-whip, whereby the Lord hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him of hie luſtful Eye which had been too ful of <hi>Adultry,</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:46511:69"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>NOw come we to the Third Head, his <hi>Examinations</hi> of himſelf in the workings of his heart relating to his Communion with God, It was not enough to this good Soul to examine himſelf only when he was approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Lords Table, on the Lords Day (as is before ſpecified) but he look'd upon it as his duty to do it every day, (both every Sabbath-day when there was no Sacrament, and every week day alſo) making it his continual daily task, as appears by his moſt Dilligent and Divine Diary. This neceſſary, but much neglected work of ſelf-tryal (I find) he began at the ſpring-time Aequinoctial upon the 10. of <hi>March</hi> 1681‥ O Holy and Happy Soul that had now his
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:46511:70"/>hard frozen heart thus kindly thaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a look of love from the <hi>Son of Righteouſneſs,</hi> as <hi>Peters</hi> was by a <hi>Look from his Lord, Luke</hi> 22.61, 62 Hereby the Lord helped him to ſay with the <hi>Bridegroom</hi> in the Song. <hi>[The winter is past the rain is over and gone, The Flowers appear on the Earth, &amp;c.]</hi> Cant. 2.10, 11, 12, 13.1 moſt bleſſed ſpring of <hi>Grace</hi> (better than that of <hi>Graſs</hi>) was now upon him, though I cannot give ſo diſtinct an account of his Diary as I would becauſe 'twas writ in obſcure Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters only with a black pencil (intended it ſeems ſolely for hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> own private uſe) yet with the be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> key we could get it hath been ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that ſuch precious treaſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould not be loſt, but communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the common good.</p>
               <p>I begin here from the Manuſcrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> both as to the matter and as to the time as I can judge, upon what Sabbat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Day I heard a Sermon upon <hi>Peter</hi>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:46511:70"/>going out and weeping bitterly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt had looked upon him. Saith he, I went to prayer that night and begged of God to give me <hi>Peters Repentanoe,</hi> and in the earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Spirit I fell flat upon the ground, before the Lord to begg it, Then I laid long till I had ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from my God, yet remained I dull and muddy till wedneſday night, and then had I ſome communion with my God again, even a new taſt of his firſt goodneſs and comfort in prayer. On Thurſday night did I meet him whom my Soul loveth again, which I found very uſeful to me, finding by woful experience that without Chriſts ſtrengthening me, I could do nothing ſpiritually, nor before the Sabbath enſuing nor in it, had I the ſweet communion with God I uſed to have before, but on Munday night I met my God having a pretty deal of time that evening, for Tueſday morning was
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:46511:71"/>not ſo good, nor could I raiſe my heart at night till it was very late, and then had I my former ſweetneſs, but much more upon wedneſday: the ſame I found upon the Sabbath following, and on Munday night and on the next night alſo, though ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dul at the firſt yet inlarg'd after upon wedneſday night I pray'd twice ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively and found more than ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry incomes: On Thurſday again I had inlargements but at the cloſe the Devil made me drowſy to cut ſhort my duty, &amp;c. but on Friday my heart was kept better raiſed: On Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day I begged of God to direct me how I might meet the bleſſing of the next Sabbath, which (through grace) I met with on that day, yet was troubled with wandrings in my evening duty: On Munday the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God was with me and made my duty ſweet at night: On Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day I met with a precious opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for my Souls good: On Wedneſday
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:46511:71"/>I did not ſo well, which made me chide my Soul for no better requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Lords kindneſs On Thur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſday morning I had Gods preſence &amp; the ſame at night though troubled with wandrings: On Friday I had many outward mercyes, yet could improve aright neither Gods word of Grace nor his works of Mercy, On Saturday (having ſpare time from buſineſs) I ſought the Lord thrice for a larger ſight of the light of his Countenance when the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath came, the Lord gave me an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of Peace,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Thus might a large account of this gracious Young-Mans <hi>Self-Tryal</hi> and watchings over his own ways from Month to Month, all along but becauſe to do ſo diſtinctly from day to day would fill a volume, I muſt therefore wave it, and that not out of Judgment only, but out of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty alſo, ſeeing the key that opened his Charactars, could not reach
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:46511:72"/>them all, neither in point of time, nor in point of matter, the judicious Reader may eaſily imagine that this defect will lame us in this work, yet though it coſt me unſpeakable trouble and pains, I ſhall follow my thread in this labyrinth.</p>
               <p>I have already given an exact ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count how he examined himſelf up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every monthly Sacrament, from <hi>Auguſt</hi> 7. 1681. to <hi>Jan.</hi> 7. 1681/3. which was the laſt he did partake of, for not long after his Dear Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer (whom he had ſo oft admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and embraced in the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per upon Earth) called him home to Sup and Feaſt with him in Heaven.</p>
               <p>As to his Self-Tryal at all other times between every one of thoſe Seventeen Sacraments, I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to relate, ſo far as my key will carry me.</p>
               <p>The beſt computation I can make out of the many manuſcripts conſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of above thirty ſheets which
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:46511:72"/>I have to abridge and methodize, drawn out of his Diary, Pocket-book and Almanack, &amp;c. He renews his ſelf-examining work again, upon <hi>March</hi> 17. 1681/2. being <hi>Fryday:</hi> how he ſpent all the time from the laſt <hi>March</hi> to this, ſave only relating to the Sacraments, we muſt be content to want it, for want of better helps, but upon that day he hath left upon record, he had wandring thoughts in duty, did little for the good of others, my ſins (ſaith he) lay but light, I mourned not for the ſins of the land, I looked not into my own heart, nor was I concern'd in holy ejaculations: The ſame he ſaith of himſelf in ſpending the 18 and <hi>March</hi> the 19. being the Sabbath, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks the ſame omiſſions, and not having a frame Suitable to the Day, yea in night-duty peſtered with wandrings: on <hi>March,</hi> 20. I aroſe from Table without drooping, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing full glad to meet God there.
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:46511:73"/>
                  <hi>March</hi> 21. had the former omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Heaven little in my ſight, 22d. day could not mourn for the ſins of the land: and the ſame frame was upon me, the 23. and 24. nor could I do better or look into my heart the 25 of <hi>March</hi> 1682. nor the ſix following Dayes of that month could he ſhake of thoſe omiſſions, <hi>April</hi> the firſt he brands himſelf with the ſame neglects: the ſecond day he adds to thoſe neglects, that wandring thoughts had eaten up the life of his duty, on the third the ſame complaint, on the fourth miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vain thoughts in a good meaſure, yet only through the ſtrenght o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt, but on fifth he adds, God our of ſight &amp; Heaven out of mind, on the ſixth he makes the ſame moan, of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, my own ſins and the ſins of the land lay too light upon my heart, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> eight, the ſame and that he had done nothing extraordinary for the Church in herday of diſtreſs. ninth
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:46511:73"/>the ſame yet had ſome good thoughts but troubled with wandrings, tenth the ſame and ſo the eleventh. adding, I have been this day tempted to <hi>pride;</hi> ſo the twelfth, thirteenth and four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth, are filled with the like com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, and fifteenth he adds I have been ſpending this noon much too vainly, the ſixteenth (being the Sabbath) he bleſſed God that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction had not dulled him in duty; 17th. had like to have fallen into paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion but God diſappointed it, yet not much in Holy Ejaculations, &amp;c. eighteenth, not up early had my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer omiſſions and commiſſions, the ninteenth, twentyeth and twenty firſt, yea to the end of <hi>April,</hi> he ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns himſelf as guilty of all thoſe aforeſaid Crimes, then <hi>May</hi> 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. Complains of all thoſe evils, adding that hurreys of his trade at this time did provoke him more to paſſion, but ſometime God helped him to ſubdue it, &amp;c.
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:46511:74"/>the 7. being Sabbath Day, ſin ſet too light, did not mourn for the ſins of the land, not enough in holy eja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations, nor in looking into my own heart, nor ſeriouſly minding the Word of God, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13. the ſame, little life, much dull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, being wearyed with the hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the World, 14, frothy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with ſome delight, O ſin ſin lay too light both mine own and the lands ſin, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19. the ſame Complaint, 20. neglecting to read Gods Word, 21, 22, 23. ſo on to the end of <hi>May,</hi> he cryes out I have done nothing for my ſelf nor the Church, I have not been my ſelf, hardly knowing what I did through the hurryes of the World, O the World, the World is a ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> impediment to my Soul, God hath not been in my mind, Heaven out of my ſight, I have not mourned for my own ſins, nor thoſe of the land nor had holy ejaculations, &amp;c. thus
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:46511:74"/>he ſaith particularly upon every day, adding thus I conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued till the fourth of <hi>June</hi> being always wearyed with work and unfit for any good, O it hath been a ſad time for my Soul, thus likewiſe I neglected till the 17 of <hi>June,</hi> on which I renewed my covenant with God, yet 18, 19. the ſame neglects prevailed, only on the 20. I had ſome holy Ejaculations, but 21, 22. the ſame and 23. I prayed not over the Sermon as I ſhould have done and omitted all as before, 24 ſtill peſtred with former neglects, O ſad, ſad that I ſhould be thus carryed under Grace, thus he moans on 25, 26. and ſo on to the end of <hi>June,</hi> on eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day I have done little for the Church, or for my Soul, have not read Gods word, ſin ſits too light, not mourn'd for my own ſin nor for the ſins of the land, Heaven hath been out of ſight and God out of mind, too little have I been in holy ejaculations,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:46511:75"/>with wandrings not oft looking into my own heart, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>July</hi> 1682. from 1 to 10. he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains particularly upon each Day in the ſame word's [too much wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings in <hi>Holy Duties,</hi> too little ſenſe of ſin upon my heart, I have not mourned enough for my own ſins nor for the ſins of the Land, not much in ejaculations, Heaven too much out of ſight, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] ſometimes adding [I neglected reading Gods Word, have done little for Gods Church have not minded my Soul nor Gods praiſe, &amp;c.]</p>
               <p>Then concludes, theſe ten days with this divine rapture. [O this deadly thing ſin hath not duely affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my heart, into what a ſad ſtate is my Soul fallen, O my God, I beſeech thee leave me not.] This ſame complaint concerning thoſe ſeveral omiſſions he carryeth on againſt himſelf quite through <hi>July,</hi> to the laſt day. <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1682. He makes
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:46511:75"/>the ſame moans of the ſame neglects all along the month upon the head of every day of the four weeks diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinctly, yet ſometimes adding, God helped me on the 2 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> againſt my deadly ſin on the 6 day (being the Sabbath) I was leſs troubled with wandrings than I was the day after, on the 8 day I aroſe from Supper with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out dropping any ſavory word at the Table, on the 11. God kept me much from my ſin this day: On the 13. I had much of God in my night prayer, though the Devil told me I had not begged Gods preſence, My dear Lord helped me to repulſe him with eaſe: On the 16 out of order all the day, but at night God ſhone upon my Soul more than a long time before: but loſt all the two following days, being hurryed with caſting up our ſhop, going backward not forward: On 19. I felt my dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſin crawl apace towards my heart, which put me upon examination,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:46511:76"/>the 20. day, and found it not in vain to caſt my burden upon the Lord, for I had thereby relief againſt my <hi>Pride</hi> &amp;c. for which I have cryed mightily to the Lord my God after which I had ſweet communion with God, then the Tempter ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tempted me to neglect hearing and reading the Word, but putting up an ejaculation, I had ſtrength to overcome him again: after hearing a Sermon I went down into the Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar to pray, where the Devil would affright me that ſomething would appear, which (through the help of my Dear Redeemer) I ſtoutly reſiſted and bid Satan defiance, then he objected againſt me my deadly ſin which I could not but own, yet could he not make me think ſo long upon it as to diſtract me in duty, which was the Devils deſign, but Oſubtil Serpent my Lords goodneſs ſtrengthned me to triumph over thee, and I had a comfortable
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:46511:76"/>ſeaſon: upon the 21 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1682. all my old neglects prevailed, and wandrings in my night prayer, but God heard my ejaculation, I got up early in the morning (which ſweet way I had much neglected through wearineſs with worldly work) to pray, wherein I found much of God, O my Soul love that lovely lovely, one thy Lord, who hath heard thee hath done, is doing great things for thee, and will do greater: On the 26. I neglected reading the Word, been too much about Worldly affairs which took me off from God, and I loſt my time in Duty, nor could I get up my thoughts to my God in my hurryes, yet on the Saturday following I recovered a bleſſed frame, O my Soul love and praiſe the Lord for ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>September</hi> the 2. I was at a faſt for the fire of London, where I was not free of my aforeſaid omiſſions, yet waiting there all the day, at length
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:46511:77"/>had the ſweet preſence of God: On the 4. I had Heaven in my ſight and but little troubled with wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings, yet too little looked I into my own heart; I ſat up late for Duty and God made it ſweet to me On the ſeventh he makes his old moan againſt himſelf ſaying, I feat my own ſelf righteouſneſs, the 10. God diſcovered my deadly ſin which cauſed his withdrawment from me; and that wiſhing to die to avoid miſery by God withdrawings, is but a pang of paſſion, The 15. old wandrings, &amp;c. returned, I think my murmuring was the cauſe: I firſt read, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.22, 23, 24. from whence upon my ejaculation God ſpake comfort to me, ſo had after delight in duty. The 19, God diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered another ſin (my ſeeking the praiſes of men) that darkned his face from me. The 23. but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſenſible how I had grieved away Gods good Spirit in morning pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:46511:77"/>The 25. had little ſenſe of Gods putting a vail over his Face toward me, which I bewailed little, the other days of this month I neglected (being out of town) to take an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of, only in the general, I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that my deadly ſin prevailed moſt, while my Soul is moſt clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>October</hi> the <hi>1ſt.</hi> my old Diſtractions. Diſturbed me running from the Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar up to the cloſet, and from thence to the cellar again yet had (through Grace) a little of Gods preſence: The 2d. I was too raſh in ſpeaking a thing that was not ſo: The 3. I was unwilling to pray in the Cellar at night, yet made willing to go, I. found much of the preſence of him who had thus inclined me; The 4. I ſpoke not of <hi>God</hi> in company of others.</p>
               <p>Yet with another Companion my <hi>God</hi> helped me to ſavoury Diſcourſe
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:46511:78"/>in prayer but then to <hi>Epſom,</hi> til the 14 day I was under dreadful deſertions which made me cry out woe is me, I have ſinned away my <hi>God,</hi> by my minding the World too much and my <hi>God</hi> too little, and by relying too much on my own ſtrength: on the 14. he renews his old complaints [Heaven out of ſight not mourned for the ſins of the land nor my own, &amp;c.] Adding roſe from Table without any thing of <hi>God</hi> there: On the 15 not ſo much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled as before with wandrings, yet ſin ſet too light, &amp;c. the 16. and 17. the ſame, The 18. and 19. bad, the 20. not ſo bad, had at night <hi>God</hi> preſence and ſome ſence of ſin, which made me burſt out crying, how have I been hopping from Mountain to hill through Simplicity, forgetting my right reſting place, O that thoſe loſt minutes and hours, had been ſpent in the ſweeteſt converſe with my Dear Redeemer, but now (from
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:46511:78"/>this time) the Lord grant great Reformation in <hi>John Draper.</hi> The 23. of <hi>October</hi> 1682. (he ſaith) I have ſtrove this day to get to <hi>God,</hi> but could not, faſted and three times prayed, ſtill the face of <hi>God</hi> was hid from me. The 24. ſtill under <hi>Gods</hi> withdrawings, ſo on 25, 26, and 28, no better with me on the 29, 30, and 31, but wandrings in duty, no right mourning for ſin, dull dead and thoughts moſtly taken up with the World, very little of <hi>God</hi> in all that I do, ſo that I knew not what to do.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>November</hi> the 1 could not gain <hi>Gods</hi> preſence, 2. the ſame, but not ſo bad in duty, 3, and 4. as bad, O ſad, ſad, ſad, but on 6. had much of <hi>Gods</hi> preſence, 8, 9, bad again, ſo 10. and 11. ſtill dull and cold, ſo 12. and 13. and endways in a ſad condition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>December.</hi> having been long out of town, half of the foregoing month
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:46511:79"/>till the fourth of this month and lived as without <hi>God,</hi> my mind taken up with the World; no longings after <hi>Gods</hi> preſence 'twas a good provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, I ſaw their worſhip at <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor</hi> which did more eſtabliſh me.</p>
               <p>This month the Lord taught me the deformity of all ſublunary things without <hi>God,</hi> now I ſee my folly, and oh that it may not be too late! I could weep night and day, for my great loſs of God; I am ſo perplex'd that I ſcarce know what to do with my ſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>January</hi> 5. 1682. I was taken ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Ill, ſo that thoſe about me, thought I was a dying, but <hi>God</hi> raiſed me up again, Oh that it might be to dye to Sin and and live to God.</p>
               <p>The 7th. (which was his ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth and laſt Sacrament-Day) makes his former moans about wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Adding, I laid in Bed too long, when I ſhould have been upon my knees, yet had more <hi>Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences</hi>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:46511:79"/>that day than for along time before, after this, was taken with a Dizzineſs in my head, like to fall down ſtairs, about 8. had a great pain in my ſide and my fit came about ten, then from day to day, lay long in bed, had little of <hi>God</hi> ſometimes forgot how it was with me; not minding my inward man enough, by diſtempers of my outward On the 22. I conſidered what I ſhould do if <hi>God</hi> call me to ſufferings and thought <hi>Gods</hi> hand was not ſhortned to ſtrengthen me as he had done all the martyrs. On 25 my cough and pain in my left ſide grew upon me ſo unfitted me for Duty yet on 30. I prayed, and had a clear ſight of <hi>God</hi> and of my Chriſt, my Dear Redeemer, Bleſſed, for ever bleſſed be his holy name.</p>
               <p>Leaſt any ponderous paſſage (out of his Diary) that might be profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to poſterity ſhould be omitted which (through the broken account
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:46511:80"/>I have of his manuſcripts) cannot eaſily be avoided, I ſhall reduce the moſt remarkable of them to thoſe <hi>Remarks,</hi> or <hi>Heads</hi> following.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Firſt Remark</hi> is, this gracious Young-Mans Diary doth plainly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim, that <hi>God</hi> made him live at the <hi>ſign of the Chequer,</hi> his life this laſt Year was ſtrangely chequered with the <hi>Black</hi> of <hi>Miſery,</hi> and with the <hi>White</hi> of <hi>Mercy,</hi> he was got into <hi>Canaan,</hi> a land of hills and valleys, now up and now down: One while mourning for <hi>Gods</hi> Abſence: and another while magnifying him for his preſence, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Second Remark,</hi> however <hi>God</hi> withdrew from him on the Week-day, yet did he moſtly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy leſt or more of <hi>God</hi> on the <hi>Sabbath</hi> as well as <hi>Sacrament</hi> Days, this I find in his own record, which was to beare up his head above water in his Conflicts.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Third Remark</hi> is, he obſerves
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:46511:80"/>Gods tenderneſs towards him in ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver withdrawing too long from him, for though he found himſelf dull and dead in duty in the morning of the Sabbath, yet found he life and warmth at evening, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> When he was comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſtay at home for keeping the houſe and ſhop (upon the Sabbath) from Sermon (he ſaith) God made that time of privacy a moſt ſweet time to him: <hi>When God denyes means, He ſupplies means.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> He Remarks, how oft he was interrupted in his private duties, being called off from them as he was a ſervant to his Maſter, which the <hi>Envious one</hi> might have an hand in, as prayer is a charm and torment to <hi>him,</hi> when <hi>God</hi> is preſent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> He notes that the low Cellar was his oratory or place of private prayer, where he ſpent many hours, without either fire or candle,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:46511:81"/>in the night, and once had the door broke open to fetch ſome candles while he was in his Devotion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seventhly,</hi> He obſerveth <hi>Gods</hi> dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings with his Soul from one Sabbath to another, and from one week day to another taking notice of all his omiſſions of good, and of all his commiſſions of evil, from <hi>Munday Morning</hi> to <hi>Saturday Night.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eightly,</hi> This was not only his practice <hi>every Week,</hi> from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the end of the Year (as is above mentioned) but alſo <hi>every Day</hi> how it was with his Soul <hi>God ward Morning, Noon</hi> and <hi>Night,</hi> and what diſcourſe at meat time alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ninthly,</hi> So ſtrict was his <hi>Scruti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> and <hi>Self-Tryal,</hi> that he ſet down once the thoughts of having a <hi>God Ring,</hi> and another time thoughts o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> getting ſome <hi>books,</hi> the Tempte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> made uſe of to juſtle out his thought of <hi>God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tenthly.</hi> So obſervant was he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:46511:81"/>all the workings of his own heart that he ſets down how that when, he was praying once in the dark Cellar without any light, the Tempter poſſeſſed him with fears that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing would appear to affright him, but <hi>God</hi> graciouſly ſtepped in, and ſaid to him, fear not thou Son of <hi>Abraham,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.1.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eleventhly,</hi> He records the very Days, wherein he miſſed his taking an account of his own daily task of ſelf examination, and when he omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſcattering of ſome ſavory diſcourſe becoming table-talk, at meat-times.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Twelfthly,</hi> He computes the very times.</p>
               <p>Firſt. When mourning for ſin was made ſweet to his Soul.</p>
               <p>Second. When he enjoyed <hi>Gods</hi> preſence in prayer both by himſelf and with others.</p>
               <p>Third. How often <hi>God</hi> came to him when diſturbed in Duty, or
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:46511:82"/>diſappointed of it, being conſtrained thereby ſometimes to pour out his heart to <hi>God</hi> in the ſhop by day, and upon his bed by Night, in both which places he had ſweet warmings of Spirit.</p>
               <p>Fourthly. How oft he made reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of his Soul to God (which was very frequent) as alſo how oft he renewed his Covenant with God eſpecially upon Sacrament Days which are the moſt Material Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks (whereof I would not omit one out of choice) I could collect out of the many ſheets I had to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe in my oft reading them over.</p>
               <p>And had not the ſame matter (ſo oft upon diſtinct occaſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated) been reduced by this method to thoſe few ſeveral Heads this tract might have ſwollen into a volume.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:46511:82"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>THE laſt ſubject of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, is twofold.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> The <hi>Evidences</hi> He had for Heaven.</p>
               <p>Second. The <hi>Characters</hi> that were given him by gracious and judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous witneſſings of others: As to the <hi>Firſt,</hi> I find ſeveral <hi>Evidences</hi> (writ with his own hand) and which gave ſweet encouragement to his Soul, that he was a choſen veſſel of mercy, and one to be filled as with <hi>Grace Here,</hi> ſo with <hi>Glory Hereafter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt. I know my <hi>Repentance</hi> (ſaith he) becauſe my ſenſe under ſin, as a burden, is heavier to my Soul, than all my afflictions are to my Body, I am aſhamed of my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:46511:83"/>ſins (which no man ſeeth or knoweth) before the Lord who ſeeth and knoweth them and all other things, and I deſire to leave my darling ſin, and to leave all love to it, yea to loath it through my love I bear to my Lord and Dear Redeemer, whom I account dearer to me than any ſin, yea than all the World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly.</hi> I know (ſaith he) that to have true faith, by Chriſt is more precious to me than all things in the World, I am willing to receive him into my heart as my Lord and King to Rule me, and my Faith works by Love ſo that I am grieved for his abſence, and rejoyce at his preſence, and I am willing to part with all for him, that he may be my all, and in all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly.</hi> I find a delight to do <hi>Gods</hi> Will, ſometimes in praying to him, ſometimes in praiſing of him, ſometimes in hearing from him, and
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:46511:83"/>ſometimes in meditating upon him, and upon that Work of mans Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly.</hi> I feel my heart mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moſt for that ſin, which moſt diſturbeth my peace, and moſt ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateth betwixt God and my Soul, and longing moſt for that mercy, that will do me moſt good in a dying hour, to wit not general, but ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al mercy, even mercy in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly.</hi> I can ſay that I love the Lord, for I hate that which grieves him, and that becauſe it grieves him; and I love thoſe that are moſt like him, yea the places and duties wherein I have found the Lord warming my heart, and cannot be content without him in any.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly.</hi> I can ſay I have a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of life ſpiritual, for I find hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grings and thirſtings after an enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and find my Soul grieved, when he is diſhonoured, either by my ſelf or by others, and
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:46511:84"/>I love, long, and look for his laſt appearing and coming.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seventhly.</hi> I highly value the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, that Word of Chriſt and Truth which bringeth good tidings, even Reconciliation and the Diſpenſation of the Grace of God which hath been hid ſome Thouſand of Years, and now is forfeited, yet graciouſly conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued to us, though withdrawn from many Nations, I am thankful for it, labour to live like it, and to adorn it with my life daily.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eightly.</hi> I know that matters are agreed with God (ſo that he is now no adverſary) becauſe I find an oneneſs with him, (1.) In mind, which is made correſpondent with the mind of God by this agreement; I can think the reproaches of Chriſt to be greater riches than the <hi>Treaſures of Aegrpt, Heb.</hi> 11.26. (2.) <hi>One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of <hi>Will,</hi> I can ſay (whether for life or Death) <hi>the will of the Lord be done, Acts.</hi> 21.14. Though there
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:46511:84"/>hath been much ado to bring my will into an agreement with God; and when I find not ſometimes an actual agreement, yet have I always an habitual agreement of my will with the will of God, (3.) <hi>Oneneſs</hi> of <hi>Affection,</hi> I love what God loves, and hate what God hates, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.70. <hi>Jer.</hi> 44.4. I hate ſin which God hates, ſo I love holineſs which God loves, (4.) <hi>Oneneſs of way: Can two walk together unleſs they be agreed? Amos</hi> 3.3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.30. and 25<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5. and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.4, 5. (5.) <hi>Oneneſs of interest,</hi> Gods Intereſt is mine and my intereſt is Gods: I can ſay (in the <hi>Witneſſings of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> Rom. 9.1.) that there is this five<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold <hi>Oneneſs</hi> betwixt God and me, ſo are agreed.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Ninth Evidence</hi> for his Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in Heaven was, his <hi>Holy Jealouſy</hi> over his own heart in all his holy undertakings, ever fearing that ſome <hi>by reſpect</hi> and not <hi>Gods glory</hi> was the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:46511:85"/>motive that led him to holy duties, this he oft prayed againſt, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly cautions a gracious Young-Man (with whom he had agreed to carry on a Chriſtian Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, either in abſence by Letter, or in preſence by Conference) that herein they did not bring <hi>hurt</hi> inſtead of <hi>good</hi> to themſelves, by ſeeking our ſelves, and not him whoſe we are, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> [We are not our own but Chriſts who pay'd dear for us, far more than we are worth, and we have covenanted to glorify him, not our ſelves, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] this <hi>Holy Jealouſy,</hi> is a bleſſed frame of Spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tenthly.</hi> His prizing an Union, and Communion with <hi>God,</hi> above the Confluence of all worldly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts. This point he (in another letter to the Young-Man aforeſaid when in the Country by ſickneſs) much inſiſts upon, ſaying, while we enjoy <hi>Gods</hi> preſence, we have the <hi>Hidden Manna,</hi> and <hi>that joy which
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:46511:85"/>ſtrangers</hi> (to God) <hi>intermeddle not not with,</hi> all is nothing and worſe than nothing without it, 'tis Heaven upon Earth, and 'tis Heaven in the way to Heaven, thus <hi>David</hi> reckon'd <hi>One Day with God better than a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand without him,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eleventhly,</hi> O <hi>What carefulneſs,</hi> do I find in all his Manuſcripts as well as in his letters expreſſed to keep his accounts <hi>even</hi> betwixt <hi>God</hi> and his Soul, that right reckoning might keep them long friends in his Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardſhip, which he deſired (himſelf and others) may give up with joy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Twelfthly.</hi> His deſire to be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and to be with Chriſt, this he repeats often in all his papers ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly longing to be out of this totte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring tabernacle and to be clothed upon with <hi>immortality</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> which deſire of his, <hi>God</hi> ſpeedily granted, finding him fully ripe for Heaven, before he was at age of 21. to lay claim to his portion here upon Earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:46511:86"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>AFter theſe ſolid Soul-ſearching Evidences, which he found in himſelf, do follow the many fair Characters, that his intimate friends (yet without flattery) give of him recorded by others: The <hi>Firſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter,</hi> was from a gracious Young-Man, (his <hi>Alter Ego</hi>) who writeth thus.</p>
               <p>I was well acquainted with Mr. <hi>John Draper</hi> for ſome Years, and the more I knew him, the more I admired him as one of the choiceſt Saints that ever I knew or ever ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to know while I live: Among many other excellencyes I took no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of him for theſe following.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> For his Solemn and Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent <hi>Dedications</hi> of himſelf to <hi>God,</hi>
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:46511:86"/>this he did from the pureſt flames of Divine Love, and from a clear viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Beauty of holineſs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly.</hi> For his frequent and ſilent <hi>Elevations</hi> of heart Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, evidenced by the often lifting of his eyes upward, conjoyned with the ſweet ſmiles of his Countenance, when he thought none obſerved it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly.</hi> For his conſtant <hi>Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> to hold communion with his <hi>God,</hi> which was ſo ſweet and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory to him that he would ſit up therein till one or two in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as his own manuſcripts mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> For his daily and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent examination of himſelf by Mr. <hi>Allens</hi> and by <hi>Pythogera's</hi> Rules, taking ſpecial notice what mercyes he daily received, what were his omiſſions of good, and commiſſions of evil that his preſent Days practice might amend the foregoing days
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:46511:87"/>error, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Hereby he aſcended to be eminent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly.</hi> For his <hi>Victory</hi> over <hi>temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,</hi> wherewith (though ſo ſtrict and one of the higheſt form in Chriſt's School) He was greatly exerciſed: I well know it coſt him much pains to conquer his conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on-ſin which through the Majeſty of <hi>God</hi> upon him (as he uſed to ſay) he prevailed over, and his other ſins at their firſt riſing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly.</hi> For his <hi>Admirable morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,</hi> The <hi>Pleaſures, Treaſures,</hi> and <hi>Honours</hi> of the World were as Dung and Droſs to him, uſing all creature-comforts in a mortified manner, ſo that it was hard for his friends to draw him to any diverſions his weaned Soul diſliked unneceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry viſits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seventhly.</hi> For his delight in Holy Duties, O what time he ſpent in <hi>prayers</hi> and <hi>praiſes,</hi> he was unweari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in thoſe Heavenly repaſts and
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:46511:87"/>Angelical imploys never contented with doing duty, till he found his <hi>God</hi> in Duty, and if diverted by buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at any time from Duty, he was reſtleſs till he could come at it, and if he met not <hi>God</hi> therein (which was but ſeldom) he found the more of <hi>Gods</hi> preſence afterward in the next, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eighthly.</hi> For his <hi>Choice of,</hi> and <hi>Carriage among</hi> his <hi>Companions:</hi> As he was very careful with whom he did aſſociate, ſo his <hi>Speech was very ſavoury,</hi> among his aſſociates. O the many gracious diſcourſes, I have heard from his mouth, as once he ſaid this to my ſelf, <hi>[Let us be burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lights in the midst of a perverſe generation]</hi> and in all companies he would be very attentive to any good diſcourſe, and retain for practice what he judged fit, and his ſpeech was a powerful charm to others ever improving his Lords talent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:46511:88"/>
                  <hi>Ninthly.</hi> For his <hi>Holy Zeal,</hi> ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly ſolliciting his aſſociates ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more to ſtedfaſtneſs in the <hi>Good old way</hi> (as he uſed to call it) having fervent love to <hi>Gods</hi> image where ever he ſaw it among differing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tenthly.</hi> For his great patience and Reſignation in his laſt ſickneſs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I was an eye-witneſs and heard him ſay, that all this viſitation was to bring him nearer <hi>God,</hi> and that divine love ſweetned all his pains and bodily decays: Never did I hear <hi>God</hi> more thanked by any Man for the higheſt confluence of pleaſing providences, than was by him for his affliction; nay never did he mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify <hi>God</hi> more in his health, than now in his ſickneſs: To conclude, He was ſuch a careful Redeemer of precious time, that he did not only not do nothing, but alſo not do little, ſo that his diligence in Holy Duties was a preſage of his ſpeedy tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:46511:88"/>into a better World, his haſty diſpatch of his Heavenly Work could not long want its reward.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Second Character</hi> I find of him was from another aſſociate and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar of his, who gives this deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> His natural temper was ſo ſweet, and his carriage ſo amica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as if nature had opened her Treaſure to adorn him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly.</hi> Though this be all that ſome attain to, yet could not he be ſatisfyed with this as his portion, nor with his deſcent of Godly Good Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, but he begged to be <hi>Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born</hi> and to be eminent for Holineſs, ſeeing ineſtimable beauty in the ways of <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly.</hi> I have admired to ſee him keep daily a ſenſible commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with <hi>God</hi> in the midſt of his Worldly affairs, being careful that all his actings had a tendency to <hi>Gods</hi> Honour.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:46511:89"/>
                  <hi>Fourthly.</hi> When he heard vain diſcourſe from others, he would drive them out of it, and perſwade them to a love to the beſt things, if he could not prevail, he would leave them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly.</hi> When in company with thoſe from whom he expected bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſcourſe, he was in pain while he met with it, telling them, ſhould all our diſcourſes be regiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, O how ſhould we be aſhamed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hereby he ſhamed them out of impertinencies, while he would ſpirituallize temporal objects.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> He was one that ſet an high value upon the ordinances of God, and was careful how he did approach to them, eſpecially the Lords Supper, Conferring with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for fitting himſelf and them for it, and every Sabbath He uſed to run over the Heads of Sermons (he heard) with me, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seventhly.</hi> He was much affected
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:46511:89"/>that his ſickneſs detained him from hearing, ſo that though his Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian perſwaded him to keep in, yet would he venture, ſaying, he got no harm thereby.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eigthly.</hi> He had an high eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on the light of Gods Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and if at any time he apprehended frowns He would give no ſleep to his eyes, &amp;c. though he ſat till midnight till he recovered the ſmiles of Gods face again, daily caſting up his accounts with God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ninthly.</hi> He ſaid to me, when I ſee Work-men tremble when they come to caſt up their accounts for fear they are not right, I think how Sinners will tremble at the great day of Account.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tenthly.</hi> He meditated much on Redemption, and crying O <hi>Eternity, Eternity, &amp;c. Ariſe ye dead and come to judgment,</hi> ſtill ſounded in his ears, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which made him keep a <hi>Diary</hi>
                  <pb n="164" facs="tcp:46511:90"/>to obſerve how grace increaſed and ſin decreaſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly.</hi> In a Word I want expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and am aſhamed I have learnt no more from ſo eminent a <hi>Patern of Piety</hi> through hopes of enjoying him longer and oftner. This made me neglect obſerving and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring many ſweet expreſſions, which now I wiſh I had not done, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Third and moſt Perfect Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter,</hi> I have from his own Gracious Siſter, who writes thus of him.</p>
               <p>My Dear Brother Mr. <hi>John Draper,</hi> was born <hi>March,</hi> 26.1663. of Godly Parents though he was much berea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of the benefit of their Education of him, they dying before he was 12. Years old, yet had they done their duty for him till then putting up many earneſt prayers to God in his behalf, which the Lord graciouſly anſwered in taking care of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs after: in the Year 1675. he was put to a School-Maſter who
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:46511:90"/>was as careful for his Soul as for his Body, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the Year 1678. He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came an apprentice, where he ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his Maſter faithfully, being effectually called in the firſt Year of his time, and then reflecting upon himſelf for his former miſpending of time, and neglecting ſeaſons of grace: He now begins to make a better improvement of the <hi>Aſſemblies Catechiſm,</hi> which he had got by heart before he was 11. Year old, at home, and the Sermons he had writ abroad at School, now became he more ſweet to us all, I never ſaw him out of an Heavenly frame, but if he was not hearing ſomething of God, he would be ſpeaking ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from God, if at any time we deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him to ſtay with us, he would anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer my time is not my own, I muſt not neglect my Maſters buſineſs, much leſs Gods, to whom I muſt give an account of all my Thoutghs, Words and deeds, I have much
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:46511:91"/>Work to do and but little time to do it in, this ſhould aw our hearts from ſin and make us earneſt for pardoning &amp; preventing mercy: O what need we have to ſtir up one another in ways of Godlineſs, for <hi>Heart-work is hard work,</hi> and we love the World more than God, He would oft bewail with tears to behold how the Youth generally prophaned the name of God and were unwearied in doing the Devils drudgery, whereas we (call'd Chriſtians) are ſoon weary with doing our Maſters will, whoſe <hi>Yoke is eaſy and his Burden light,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, 'tis free grace that makes the difference betwixt us and thoſe Vain Youths. He expreſſed his fear of ſetting up for himſelf often, obſerving how many were Zealous while <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices,</hi> yet declined when became <hi>Masters,</hi> who being asked why they had loſt their firſt love, anſwered it was for want of time, to which he replyed it was more for want of
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:46511:91"/>
                  <hi>love</hi> than of <hi>time,</hi> this he feared might be his own caſe if God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented it not. Being asked if he were willing to ſuffer for God, he anſwered, if God call me to it he will quallifie me for it, but he thought God would not put that honour upon him: The time that others take for recreation, he ſpent in holy Duties, and the money others ſpend idelly he laid out either profitably or charitably. His ſickneſs began <hi>Jan.</hi> 23. 1682. which he bore with wonderful patience all along.</p>
               <p>Ever deſiring <hi>God</hi> would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat his work in and upon him, O how would he bleſs <hi>God</hi> that it fared well with his Soul, how ever it fared with his Body, and that <hi>God</hi> was never wanting to us, when we are not wanting to our ſelves, though ſome blamed him for being too bookiſh during his weakneſs, he anſwered, ſhould reading impair my health, I am ſure it refreſhes my
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:46511:92"/>Soul, and I wiſh you all to prize Communion with <hi>God,</hi> and to make your peace with <hi>God</hi> before the night come, had I now that work to do, I might expect frowns where (through my Dear Redemer) I have ſmiles upon me, which I cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs.</p>
               <p>When in the greateſt extremity, He would ſay, what is all this, to that which <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſuffered for me, crying out, O the gentleneſs of <hi>God</hi> to me compared with <hi>Crhiſts</hi> ſorrows calling to hear the 14, 15, 16, and 17. Chapters of <hi>John,</hi> read to him when weakeſt he would lay ſmiling with his eyes and his hands lift up to Heaven, and a few days before he dyed he ſaid thus to me, <hi>Siſter</hi> I know you wiſh me well, I cannot be well here, therefore be willing to let me go, 'tis not long ſince <hi>God</hi> made you willing to leave me in a troubleſome World, and now will not you be willing to give me up to
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:46511:92"/>
                  <hi>God:</hi> if a taſt of Heaven be ſo ſweet here, what is the full injoyment, let me go firſt, 'tis but a little time and we ſhall meet again, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I have forborn to mention my death (to the loſs of my ſelf and others) becauſe your ſpirit cannot bear it, O how am I comforted in the ſtock of prayers going for me, when I cannot now pray for my ſelf, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is interceding for me in Heaven: After this his ſpeech was ſcarce intelligible, yet under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood he ſaid, <hi>[Lord thou knoweſt what I have done, and what I have left undone,]</hi> oft over, and all night ſpake with ſuch earneſtneſs as thinking he was underſtood, the next morning friends perſwaded me to withdraw as being no more uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to him, but hurtfull to my ſelf, and if he became more ſenſible it would grieve him to ſee me grieve, But after ſome hours abſence, return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him, he took me by the hand
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:46511:93"/>to comfort me ſaying, with Arms ſpread, my <hi>God</hi> hath chained up Satan, which was an anſwer to that very requeſt, put up for him a little before. Thus when death (<hi>That King of terrours,</hi> and terrour of Kings) was unſtung, he ſubmitted to its ſtroke and changed his life for a better. <hi>Aug.</hi> 3. 1682.</p>
               <p>He appointed the Text for his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Sermon to be <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.9. (as is related before) in the time of his Health, yet finding the ſentence of Death upon himſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He was born 1663. began his laſt ſickneſs on <hi>Jan.</hi> 23. and dyed when <hi>Auguſt</hi> was but 3. days old.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>This Bleſſed Soul paſſed from Three to Three,</l>
                  <l>Handed by <hi>Three in one</hi> the <hi>Trinity,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From Womb to Tomb. <hi>Three threes</hi> compleats his race,</l>
                  <l>Turns all his griefs to everlaſting Peace.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="171" facs="tcp:46511:93"/>The <hi>Next Character</hi> is that of a <hi>Miniſter</hi> who writes thus to him in his laſt ſickneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Shall I be ſorry to hear of your ſickneſs? I am, as it is an evil to <hi>Nature,</hi> but I rejoyce in hope that it will increaſe your <hi>Grace,</hi> not doubting but to ſuch a ſerious Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian and Religious perſon as you have been, this Affliction will be the taking away of ſin, and this rod (with <hi>Aarons</hi>) will bloſſom with the <hi>Peaceable fruits of Righteouſneſs,</hi> your great knowledge in the myſtery of Salvation, and eminent proficiency in the School of Chriſt may well put a <hi>Superſedeas</hi> to any inſtructions from me, yet give me leave as a faithful Monitor to mind you of your duty of <hi>Patience,</hi> that you may be as eminent in that Grace in the time of your ſickneſs, as you were in other Graces in the time of your health. I know 'tis impoſſible for <hi>Nature</hi> to endure (without murmuring) the
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:46511:94"/>loſs of ſuch a mercy as health, but <hi>Grace</hi> can weigh theſe <hi>Conſiderations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> Conſider who is the Author of your affliction, it ſprings not out of die duſt, nor comes by chance, but 'tis my Fathers hand that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points the <hi>time, place, meaſure,</hi> and <hi>manner,</hi> ſo muſt not <hi>murmur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Second. Conſider,</hi> though you be <hi>a Son of God,</hi> yet your ſin has deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Hell, and thither had you been caſt, had not your Dear Redeemer dyed for you: But ſeeing you are <hi>Delivered from wrath to come,</hi> and this is all your Hell you are like to have, to wit, this preſent chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, therefore you may not mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Third. Conſider</hi> God never <hi>Afflicts willingly,</hi> but when <hi>need is,</hi> and for gracious ends, to ſubdue ſin and to ſtrengthen Grace, to wean from the World, and to make Heaven more deſirable, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (his bowels ſtill year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning while his rod is on our backs)
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:46511:94"/>if this be ſo, ſhould you not be <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourth. Meditate</hi> much on the joys of Heaven, and the happy reſt there prepared for you, which tranſcends our apprehenſions while we taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle in houſes of clay. O the Rivers of pleaſure, the Manſions of bliſs, the Regions of happineſs, the Crowns of life, the ſcepters of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the Robes of Glory, and the thrones of honour, that are there prepared for the Lambs followers, no ſinning is there to provoke God, no ſuffering to moleſt us, no weeping eyes, ſighing breaſts, or complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tongues are found there. No crying there [<hi>O my Head! my Head, and O my bowels be pained,</hi> &amp;c.] But all reſt in the arms of love, and in the Boſom of Chriſt. O happy Souls that are now got thither, and ſince you will ſhortly be there, ſhould you not be ſubmiſſive to and rejoyce in the will of God: That he
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:46511:95"/>give you both an Happy and a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable departure out of <hi>time</hi> into <hi>eternity</hi> is the prayer of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The laſt <hi>Character</hi> is that of <hi>mine own</hi> from my own perſonal knowledg of him, which, though it was not ſo much as was that of many others who were more converſant with him, yet was enough to give me a proſpect of his (almoſt) unparallel'd piety: I never converſed with a more mortifyed Young-Man from youthful vanitys, ſo ſerious in his deportments, ſo ſavoury in his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes with ſo grave an aſpect, and and ſo compoſed a countenance, as I ſeldom law in this our <hi>Engliſh Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el.</hi> He had ſo faithfully followed theſe following rules.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> Let not God find me in my bed when he looks for me on my knees.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Second.</hi> Nor wandring thoughts eat out the life of my Duty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Third.</hi> Nor be ſlight in reading
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:46511:95"/>
                  <hi>Gods</hi> Word, or hearing it preached, which I ſhould digeſt in my heart, and repeat in my life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourth.</hi> I muſt redeem time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifth.</hi> Deny my ſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixth.</hi> Do more than others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seventh.</hi> Be careful of my compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eighth.</hi> Leave the Savour of Grace behind me in all companies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ninth.</hi> Be Holy in all my relations as a <hi>ſervant, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tenth.</hi> No ſin muſt ſit light.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eleventh.</hi> Nor may I live in that which I know or fear to be a ſin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Twelfth.</hi> 'Tis my duty to mourn for ſin, my own and others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirteenth.</hi> To be much in Holy Ejaculations, having God oft in my mind, and Heaven oft in my ſight.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourteenth.</hi> To be oft looking into my own heart.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifteenth.</hi> To reſiſt the firſt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of ſin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixteenth.</hi> To bridle my tongue.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="176" facs="tcp:46511:96"/>
                  <hi>Seventeenth.</hi> To feed in Gods fear at my meal times.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eighteenth.</hi> To do all my ſecular and ſacred affairs for Gods glory, the good of others as well as my ſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That he familliarizing his Soul with theſe and the like helps, and duely and daily weighing himſelf in the ballance of the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> ſoon became a <hi>None ſuch,</hi> in Chriſtian attainments, ſo that <hi>the way of this Godly-wiſe Young-Man</hi> was <hi>above</hi> (as <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.24.) Raiſing the feet of his Soul to walk in a higher Region and above the heads of moſt other young-men: Sure I am <hi>his Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was in Heaven</hi> (as <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20.) while his <hi>commoration</hi> was on <hi>Earth.</hi> the <hi>Rabbins</hi> ſay, that <hi>Cain's</hi> ſin was not <hi>dividing aright for God,</hi> for which fault (they ſuppoſe) God brought that brand (of going about <hi>everſighing</hi> and <hi>trembling, &amp;c.</hi> but I may without vanity affirm, that if any young man learned to divide
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:46511:96"/>aright betwixt his <hi>General</hi> and <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular calling,</hi> this Holy Young-man did, who ſeldom (or never) would ſuffer them to juſtle out one the other. As he would not give his <hi>Masters-time</hi> to <hi>Gods worſhip,</hi> ſo nor <hi>Gods time</hi> to his <hi>Maſters ſervice:</hi> I wiſh all apprentices would learn to write after ſo fair a copy, and to dreſs themſelves by ſo lovely a look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-glaſs, I know alſo how the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God reſted upon him in moſt eminent actings and emanations, and I ſtand admiring, not only at his moſt Evangelical <hi>Experiences, Exerciſes, Examinations,</hi> and <hi>Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences</hi> above mentioned, but alſo at his moſt ſenſible and ſavoury letters not only writ with his own <hi>Mortal hand,</hi> but with a moſt <hi>Gracious Heart.</hi> In one of which I find how he obliged his Correſpondent (a Godly Young man) to Holineſs with theſe arguments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First.</hi> We have covenanted not
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:46511:97"/>to allow our ſelves in any known ſin but to uſe all means for the death and deſtruction thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Second.</hi> To forſake all that is dear to us in this world, rather than forſake God and his Goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Third.</hi> To watch over our own hearts againſt the temptations both of proſperity and adverſity leaſt we be drawn from God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourth.</hi> To take the Laws of God for the rule of our thoughts, words and actions, ſquaring our whole life thereby.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifth.</hi> To neglect nothing we know to be our duty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixth.</hi> To reſign up our ſelves to God and avouch him for our Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seventh.</hi> To own <hi>Jehovah</hi> as our portion, promiſing to ſerve him all our days.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eight.</hi> To improve Chriſt as he is the new and living way for acceſs to the Father.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="179" facs="tcp:46511:97"/>
                  <hi>Ninth.</hi> To be marryed to Chriſt, accepting him for our Head and Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band in all ſtates and times taking our lot as it falls, though ſufferings and death do accrue, we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce our own will and wiſdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In another I find the <hi>Saints pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt. <hi>What Chriſt is to us?</hi> He is <hi>Our Lord,</hi> 1. Cor. 1, 2. Our <hi>Friend,</hi> Cant. 5.16. <hi>Our fleſh and blood,</hi> Heb. 2.14. Our <hi>Brother,</hi> Ver. 17. Our <hi>Father,</hi> Iſa. 63.16. Our <hi>Husband</hi> Rom. 7.4. <hi>what we are to Chriſt?</hi> His <hi>Servants</hi> Rom. 6.22. His <hi>Friends,</hi> John. 15.14. His <hi>Kinſmen,</hi> Mark 3.21.35. His <hi>Brethren,</hi> John 7.3. His <hi>Sons.</hi> Gal. 3.26. His <hi>Spouſe, Siſter, Love</hi> and <hi>Dove,</hi> Cant. 4.9. The Church is one <hi>Vine,</hi> John 15. 1. One <hi>Seed,</hi> Gal. 3.16. One <hi>Temple,</hi> Eph. 2.16. One <hi>Body,</hi> Rom. 12.5. One <hi>Spirit,</hi> 1. Cor. 6.16. and one <hi>Christ,</hi> 1. Cor.
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:46511:98"/>12.12. and upon the ſurvey of this <hi>Pedigree,</hi> he Cryeth out, <hi>Lord what is man</hi> thou art thus mindful of him, making him (in ſome reſpects) Higher than Angels, Thou haſt crowned him with Glory and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, <hi>&amp;c. Pſal.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>In another letter to his elder Siſter (writ about three a clock in the morning) he gives an high encomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um of Godlineſs (to ſtrengthen her in love to the good ways of God) ſaying, 'tis the great work we have to mind in this lower World, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore need we to meet helps to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward one another therein, 'tis not a ſmall thing, or a by-buſineſs to be forgotten, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'tis the beſt riches that cannot be taken from us, as there are all good things in it, ſo there is no danger to looſe it, yet find I a proneneſs to be triffling and tampe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with tranſitory vanities, while the true riches are neglected, O this <hi>Heart-work</hi> is <hi>Hard-work,</hi> and the
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:46511:98"/>way to Heaven is up the hill, but our Captain (if we follow him cloſe) will make it eaſy, helping us to hold on and to hold out to the end not only as <hi>living</hi> but alſo as <hi>lively Christians,</hi> not loitering in the way of ſin, but luſtily running our race, ſeating our ſelves under Gods eye: All lower perſons and things be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable, Relations may be our friends to Day and they may be dead to morrow, or they may live, yet their love may die, and our delights to day may be our ſorrow and our horror to morrow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but ſtill in Godlineſs we have an unchangable God, our thoughts of this muſt be bellows to blow up the flame of our deſires, and the ſpur to our dull affections.</p>
               <p>In another Letter to his younger Siſter (which came alſo to my hand) O what a travelling ſpirit was upon him, that Chriſt may beformed in her, ſaying to her.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="182" facs="tcp:46511:99"/>My hearts deſire and prayer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that you may be ſaved, con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>der your ſad eſtate by nature, you are a ſlave of Satan, a ſtranger to God, and if you dye in that eſtate you are undone for ever. O that you may ſee in this your day the things that belong to your everlaſting peace, leaſt they be for ever hid from your eyes. For judgment will certainly find you, where death doth leave you, if you die in an unregenerate ſlate, you will be baniſhed from the preſence of God, and an eternity of horror and terrour is to be endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But if you <hi>make your calling and election ſure,</hi> then may you expect, nay you will have everlaſting bliſs. O think much on theſe things you have now time to make your peace, put it not off (if you love your Soul) no not till to morrow (as too many young perſons do thinking it ſoon enough yet and yet) but know, you may be dead before
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:46511:99"/>the morrow, pray therefore for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing Grace and for power to caſt off ſin, eſpecially that which lays neareſt your heart, for if the heart-ſin be loved better than Chriſt 'twill undo you for ever, let but your Lord have your chiefeſt love and you will ſoon find more pleaſure in ways of holineſs than in all the ways of ſin.</p>
               <p>In another letter to his kinſwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, I find him very warm in his exhortations, ſaying.</p>
               <p>Now is the time of ſtirring up one another to prepare for approaching evils, ſeeing the Cloud thickens and looks black over our head, we have need to have our rock ready to fly to and to have our evidences for Heaven cleared, to have our loins girt and our lamps burning, and to ſit looſe from thoſe lower things that ſeem now to be leaving us, O that ſweet word <hi>Draw nigh to God,</hi> and <hi>he will draw nigh to us,</hi> for the end
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:46511:100"/>of this diſpenſation is to drive u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> further off from ſin and nearer God. And O ſweet word, <hi>In the world ye ſhall have tribulation, but in Chriſt peace,</hi> who would not travel through a world of trouble, to find that peace in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>This kinſwoman was ſo touched with his lines, that ſhe caſt in this character of him after his death, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, God took him from me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I was unworthy of him, he told me, 'twas better to want time than to want an heart for doing good, he cryed oft (hearing the clock ſtrike) O <hi>Time, Time,</hi> I am ſo much nearer eternity, and O the Love of Chriſt that purchaſed an eternity of weal for me, is there any Love like Chriſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In another I find theſe ſhort rules (comprized in Verſe) very uſeful to him when time would not permit him to make any uſe of larger helps.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="175" facs="tcp:46511:100"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Let not ſoft ſleep thy weary eyes invade</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Before the ſame confine with the nights ſhade.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thy thoughts retire, and make it their laſt task</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of the days deeds three queſtions thus to ask.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wherein Have I tranſgreſſed this day? what good deed have I wrought,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And what have I forborn to do? which to have done I ought?</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>Or Thus.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>What have I done amiſs this day? What well?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>What Good have I omitted?</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience tell?</l>
               </q>
               <p>This Diſtich (as his who ſent him them intimates) comprehends all our thoughts words and deeds, and by pondering and improving them duely
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:46511:101"/>and daily, they both reaped great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In another I find that the method of correſpodency betwixt his Friend (a gracious young man) and himſelf was carryed on by a <hi>communication of Experiences</hi> or prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical and profitable diſcourſes upon the <hi>joys of Heaven,</hi> the love of God in Chriſt, the ſecond coming of our Lord, the evil of ſin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As to the firſt of thoſe points, <hi>(the joys of Heaven)</hi> their intercourſe maketh this mention.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Glory</hi> (which we ought to have our Faith fixed on for our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort) is called in Scripture compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: <hi>A Crown of life, of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and of Glory, an incorruptible inheritance, a reſt for the People of God, the recompence of reward, an Houſe not made with hands, an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent place which the eye hath not ſeen,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The City of the Living God, the Heavenly Jeruſalem, the Holy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:46511:101"/>the Bleſſed hope and end of our holy race, the City whoſe builder and maker is God, the houſe not made with hands, the heavenly Country, the ſtrait Gate,</hi> &amp;c. The contemplation of all theſe divne compariſons afforded ſtrong conſolation to Both their Souls, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No leſs comfortable was their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terchange of communion about the other point of <hi>Christs ſecond coming,</hi> which is likewiſe called in Scripture a <hi>Day of conſolation, and of corronati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, an harveſt day a marriage day, and a day of admiration,</hi> wherein Chriſt will be admired of all his Saints at his <hi>Glorious appearance,</hi> though now we be diſpiſed by the world as our dear Redeemer (him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was) yet, this is our joy our redemption day draweth nigh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In another letter he hath this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage (I ſuppoſe) to ſome <hi>Miniſter,</hi> ſaying, Sir, though I be a ſtranger to
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:46511:102"/>you, yet cannot, nay dare not ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> any longer from ſpeaking to you; for asking my own heart whether I were fit to dye it was anſwered that could not be till accounts were clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (concerning the ſins I groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under) between God and my Soul, about this Sir, my preſent addreſs is for your profitable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: Therefore I beſeech you ſearch me throughly to the very inwards of my heart, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Many more ſuch ſavoury lines (all ſeaſoned with the ſalt of ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſanctity, I might add out of ſeveral other of his Letters, which muſt be omitted to avoid prolix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity.</p>
               <p>To Conclude, upon the View of the whole, I muſt only add this though we have not his picture drawnin paint by ſome skilful limner for refreſhing the memory of Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:46511:102"/>and to prefix before this Book, yet it is limned to the life in black and white both by pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Chriſtians, and publick Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters: He was (without flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) a mirror of piety eſpecially in making ſo ſtrict a ſcrutiny over all his own ſteps, and taking ſo ſerious a proſpect over all his own works both upon Sabbath days and upon every week-day between them, that <hi>He might keep his heart with all diligence,</hi> Prov. 4.23. O how exact was he in <hi>Self-Examination,</hi> as well in civil and ſecular, as in ſacred affairs, <hi>I have been young,</hi> and <hi>now am old,</hi> yet never in all my acquaintance found I ſo much faithful Self-tryal which is indeed a moſt neceſſary, but alas a much neglected duty, and I am confident moſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are at a great loſt in their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner man by the omiſſion hereof, as to my own part, I am utterly
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:46511:103"/>aſhamed to behold my ſelf (now an old Miniſter of Forty Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs ſtanding in the Miniſtry) ſo far out ſtripped by ſo Young a Man (not attaining the third part of my age) and ſo private a Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian as an Apprentice; would to God, we could all (young and old, Miniſters and People) imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate this Pattern of piety, calling our faithleſs hearts to a faithfull account daily, and ever keeping upon our Watch-Tower, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This would be a bleſſed means <hi>to keep in the fear of God all the day,</hi> Prov. 23.17. to live much more in a little time, as he did from 1678. to 1683. to be neither <hi>aſhamed to live,</hi> nor <hi>afraid to dye,</hi> like him, who lived his little ſhort life with Chriſt in this lower world, and now reigneth with Chriſt in the upper and better world.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:46511:103"/>
            <head>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I did dilligently correct every Sheet yet for want of ſome Reviſes, theſe faults with ſome others have eſcaped.</head>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>In the Epiſtle page 5. line 18. <hi>dele</hi> 6 p. 6. l. 24. read <hi>got.</hi> p. 36. l. 18. <hi>to wit.</hi> tranſ. p. 49. l. 9. for <hi>third</hi> r. <hi>threefold.</hi> p. 63. l. 20. for <hi>Heaven</hi> r. <hi>haven.</hi> P. 77. 1. 21. for <hi>ſoul</hi> r. <hi>ſeal.</hi> p. 79. 1. 17. r. <hi>than.</hi> p. 108. 1. 6. r. <hi>get.</hi> p. 116. 1. 21. r. <hi>jeered,</hi> and 1. 24. r. <hi>that.</hi> p. 150. 1. 12. for <hi>to</hi> r. <hi>I.</hi> for <hi>by</hi> r. <hi>becauſe.</hi> p. 170. 1. 9. for 82. r. 83.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
